<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Truth vindicated against all heresies shewing how the seed of the woman and the seed of the serpent is distinguished : the woman cloathed with the sun discoverd, she having the moon under her feet : the Old and New Testament made to agree and God's justice and mercy magnified.</title>
            <author>Marsin, M.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 196 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63780</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3162</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32876</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12775470</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12775470</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93759</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63780)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93759)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1538:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Truth vindicated against all heresies shewing how the seed of the woman and the seed of the serpent is distinguished : the woman cloathed with the sun discoverd, she having the moon under her feet : the Old and New Testament made to agree and God's justice and mercy magnified.</title>
                  <author>Marsin, M.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>108 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by Edward Pool ... Abel Roper ... Mr. Michael ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Second ed. (1700) has statement of resposibility : by M. Marsin.</note>
                  <note>First edition.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages 57-68 lacking; pages cropped and tightly bound with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal.</term>
               <term>Eschatology.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93759:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TH Vindicated, Againſt All HERESIES, SHEWING How the
<hi>Seed</hi> of the <hi>Woman,</hi> and the <hi>Seed</hi> of the
<hi>Serpent</hi> is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed. THE Woman cloathed with the
<hi>Sun</hi> diſcovered, ſhe having the <hi>Moon</hi> under her Feet. The
Old and New Teſtament made to agree. AND God's JUSTICE and MERCY
Magnified.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and Sold by <hi>Edward Pool</hi> at the
Sign of the <hi>Half Moon</hi> under the <hi>Royal Exchange. Abel Roper</hi> at
the <hi>Black Boy,</hi> over againſt St. <hi>Dunſtan's</hi> Church,
<hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi> Mr. <hi>Michael</hi> at the <hi>Crown</hi> and
<hi>Cushion</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall:</hi> And at <hi>Mercer's</hi>
Chappel in <hi>Cheapſide.</hi> 1698.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:93759:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:93759:2"/>
            <p>I have by God's aſſiſtance, made plain the true meaning of
this Text, which I found to be much abuſed by one, who in his Book, ſaith,
He knows not but that he may be the <hi>Elias</hi> which was to come. And he in
his Book has thrown the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage of the Devil and Man upon God, upon the
miſtakes of this and ſome other miſtaken places of Scripture. By which
miſtaken places, the Prince of Darkneſs has got wonderful advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, to
the deſtruction of many thouſand poor Souls.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <head>I. Chap.</head>
            <p>GEN. 3.22. <hi>And the Lord God ſaid, Behold the man is become
as one of us, to know good and evil: And now leaſt he put forth his Hand, and
take alſo of the Tree of Life, and eat and live for ever.</hi> Now in that
God ſaid, Behold, the Man is become as one of us, to know go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> and evil. That was, the Man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came
like God in the knowledge of good and evil. For God had the knowledge of good
and evil, to diſtinguiſh between the excellency of the one, and the
abomination of the other. For God was of purer Eyes than to behold Iniquity,
<hi>Hab.</hi> 1.13. That is, to behold either the Pride or Malice of the Devil,
or the evil of Man, with approbation. And <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> when
they had eaten of the forbidden Fruit, they became aſhamed of the Evil they
had done, whereby their Nakedneſs was diſcovered to them. And ſo the Evil
of Sin became diſliked by them. And in that <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi>
diſliked Sin, and liked Good, therein they became like God, in the knowledge
of good and evil: In that they diſliked the one, and loved the other, tho'
not in that perfect degree, yet unto God it might bear a reſemblance. For Man
was at firſt created in the <pb n="4" facs="tcp:93759:3"/>Image of God, yet infinitely
ſhort of the glorious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of God, who is an unchangeable Being, and
beyond the Power of Satan's deceiving. But <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> being
aſhamed of what they had done, therein they were quite contrary to the Devil,
for he was without ſhame, and without excuſe. For whatſoever Evil he
commits, he never is ſurprized or drawn into it; but he always doth the
worſt of Evils with his beſt liking. And whatever Wickedneſs he does, he
is the Father of it, <hi>John</hi> 8.44. And not that the Evil of Sin was
firſt determined by God, as is falſly aſſerted by ſome. Now
<hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> were beguiled and drawn into the Snare by the
Devil. And he endeavoured to enſuare our bleſſed Lord, when he ſaid,
<hi>If thou be the Son of God, caſt thy ſelf down, for it is written, He
ſhall give his Angels charge concerning thee, and in their Hands they ſhall
bear thee up, leaſt at any time thou daſh thy Foot againſt a Stone,</hi>
Mat. 4.6. So likewiſe Satan uſed perſwaſions to <hi>Adam</hi> and
<hi>Eve,</hi> in ſetting forth how beneficial the eating of that Tree would
be to them: And then ſhe apprehended it was a Tree to be deſired to make
one wiſe. And Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is pleaſing to God and Man: And he that hateth
Underſtanding, is a Fool, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 3.9,10. <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.22. And
it was by Satan's plauſible Inſinuations that he deceived them, he telling
them <hi>They ſhould be as Gods, knowing Good and Evil.</hi> And that God did
but threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten them, and that <hi>they ſhould not ſurely dye, Gen.</hi> 3.4.
So he beguiled them, and they did eat; but not as they had any diſlike to
good, or delight in evil, but the contrary; for he perſwaded them, they
ſhould be like Gods, or God: and when they ſaw by what they had done, that
their Natures were defiled, ſo as thereby their Nakedneſs did appear to
them, they were aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. And where there remains Fear and Shame, there
remains a Child-like frame: Now <hi>Adam</hi> beholding his Sin with fear and
Shame. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.7.10. He there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93759:3"/>ſhewed his
diſlike to Sin. And therefore God had compaſſion on Man, and promiſed
him a Saviour. And in the State that <hi>Adam</hi> was then in, God ſaw a
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability that he might ſtill take and eat of the Tree of Life, and
therefore the Lord ſent him forth of the Garden, leaſt he ſhould put
forth his Hand and take alſo of the Tree of Life, and eat and live for ever,
<hi>Gen.</hi> 3.22,23. the which God, before they had Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, gave them free
liberty to do. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.16. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God determined not Mans
miſcarriage, by not putting him in ability capable to ſtand, as ſome have
falſly imagined. But God having ſaid before to <hi>Adam,</hi> that <hi>in
the Day that he did eat of the Tree of knowledge of Good and evil, he ſhould
ſurely die. Gen.</hi> 2.17. And it being impoſſible for God to lye,
<hi>Heb.</hi> 6.18. Therefore God ſent them out of the Garden, leaſt they
ſhould take hold of the Tree of Life, and eat, and live for ever. And God
rather chooſing to part with the Son of his Love from the Throne of his Glory
to Suffer for Sinners, his Love to his Creatures made that poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible; but
for God to lye, is impoſſible. Therefore <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> for his
tranſgreſſion dyed in the day of a Thouſand Years. For one day is with
the Lord as a Thouſand Years, and a Thouſand Years as one day. 2.
<hi>Pet.</hi> 3.8. And for the Sin of <hi>Adam</hi>'s tranſgreſſion,
there was but the puniſhment of this Life, and Death pronounced againſt
them, with a comfortable promiſe by the Seed of the Woman. <hi>Gen.</hi>
3.15,16,17,18,19. but the Fire of Hell was not threatned to them, neither was
Hell Fire prepared for Man, but for the Devil and his Angels, <hi>Matt.</hi>
25.41. who before the Creation of the World rebelled.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Now there is a great deal of difference in Scripture
between the meaning of the Creation of the World, and the Foundation of the
World: there being but one Creation of the World, but ſeveral Foundations, 
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93759:4"/>in as much as there was made ſeveral Worlds, <hi>Heb.</hi>
1.2. As the Old World, This World, and the World that is yet to come. All
having ſeveral Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations. <hi>Adam</hi> being the Foundation of the Old
World; <hi>Noah</hi> the Foundation of this World; And <hi>Abraham</hi> the
Foundation of the World to come. So as all that come in heirs to that World,
muſt come in as the Seed of <hi>Abraham. Gal.</hi> 3.28. And as the Twelve
Tribes are the Foundation of the World to come; ſo the Twelve Apoſtles are
ſaid to be the Foundation of the Heavenly City, having their names writ on
the wall thereof, <hi>Reve.</hi> 21.14. And the Twelve Tribes when they were
brought out of <hi>Egypt</hi> to be placed in the Heart of the Earth, and to be
laid for the Foundation of the World to come, at which Foundation Chriſt was
figuratively ſlain in the Paſchal Lamb. But was fore-ordained to be ſlain
before the Foundation of the World. Which Foundation, is that before mentioned;
and therefore God proved and tryed <hi>Abraham</hi> to ſee whether he would
offer his only Son as a Sacrifice to him, before he made him that Promiſe,
<hi>that in his Seed all the Nations of the Earth ſhould be Bleſſed,</hi>
Gen. 22.16,17,18. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15. Which Promiſe will be made good in
time to come, and then will be put in Subjection to Chriſt the World to come.
<hi>Heb.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.13,14.26,27. At which Foundation, the Works
of thoſe unbelieving <hi>Jews</hi> were finiſhed, when they refuſed to go
to fight for the Land of <hi>Canaan.</hi> And from that Foundation, after that
miſcarriage, God elected a Remnant. And they are thoſe of whom it is
ſaid, <hi>they were choſen from the Foundation.</hi> And the peculiar
People choſen from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> which likewiſe had the
peculiar call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and alſo were to receive the Holy Ghoſt to be in them,
which was the anointing of the Spirit, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they ſpake with Tongues, and
wrought Miracle, that thereby they might be alſo a light to the World 
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93759:4"/>theſe were they of whom it is ſaid, they were choſen
before the Foundation of the World, which Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is <hi>Iſrael.</hi> And
God choſe them as to matter of choice and liking, before the Body of
<hi>Iſrael,</hi> which were the Foundation, becauſe they had wilfully
diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed him but as to the matter of Time, long after. Whereas the
Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>They were choſen in Chriſt before the World
was.</hi> That is, before the World was, which is now to come, in which they
are to receive the promiſed Bleſſing. And as to what God ſaid
concerning <hi>Jocob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> before they had done Good or
Evil, was only that <hi>the Elder ſhould Serve the Younger;</hi> and not that
God did ever hate his Creature, until ſuch time as they wilfully diſobeyed
him. But theſe words con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> have a
far other meaning then what we have hitherto apprehended. But this and the
other miſtaken places of Scripture, by which the World has been caſt into a
miſt of Darkneſs, I have now by Gods aſſiſtance, by laying the
Scriptures together, made the true meaning of the word appear, as may be found
in my Book, lately Publiſhed. But St. <hi>Peter</hi> fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly warns us, That
in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles are things hard to be underſtood. (Which
thoſe that were unlearned in the Scriptures did wreſt, as they alſo did
ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Scriptures, to their own deſtruction. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16.)
But the Scriptures rightly underſtood, and believed, are able to make us
wiſe unto Salvation. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. Whereas St. <hi>James</hi>
ſaith, <hi>Known unto God are all his works, from the beginning of the
World,</hi> Acts. 15.18. From which words it is clear, that all Gods works were
not known to him before the beginning of the World. And that is was then the
works that properly belong to God, that were known to him. And that the
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the World, the Apoſtle here ſpeaks of, muſt have its chief
reference to the beginning or Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the World, that was laid in the
Seed of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:93759:5"/>when God brought them out of the
Land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> to place them in the Heart of the Earth for the
beginning or Foundation of the World to come, as by his forementioned words
doth appear, and not that he had his reference to the beginning of the
Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the World, or the beginning of the World in <hi>Adam</hi> after
the Fall. For the Apoſtle ſpeaking how God did at firſt viſit the
<hi>Gentiles</hi> to take out of them a People for his Name. <hi>Acts.</hi>
15.14. Which were them to whom the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> was given to be in
them. <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. And they to whom the Holy Ghoſt was given, were to
be a light to the World, that the world might believe that God had ſent
Chriſt, <hi>John.</hi> 17.21. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which 'tis ſaid, he will return and
Build again the Tabernacle of <hi>David</hi> which is Fallen down,
<hi>Acts.</hi> 15.16. The which will be when the Lord returns; Whom the Heavens
muſt receive until the times of the Reſtitution of all things, which God
hath ſpoken by the Mouth of all his Prophets ſince the World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan.
<hi>Acts.</hi> 3.21. And then in his following words he tells us who the
beginning of this forementioned world were. That it was the Fathers in the
Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. <hi>verſ.</hi> 22. (For <hi>Moſes</hi> truly ſaid unto the
Fathers, a Prophet ſhall the Lord your God raiſe up unto you, of your
Bretheren, him ſhall ye hear in all things,) the which will be when the Lord
again comes. And then will be <hi>Iſrael's</hi> Glory, and then the World
that is to come will be in Subjection unto Chriſt. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5. And
theſe are the works, St. <hi>James</hi> had his chief reference to, when he
ſaid, <hi>known unto God are all his works from the beginning of the
World.</hi> Acts 15.18. Which beginning of the World, was as is aforeſaid.
And the Eternal pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſpoken of, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.11. Only reacheth
forward to the Eternity that lies before us. As Chriſt in time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the
Author of Eternal Salvation: And as in time he promiſed Eternal Life. And
whereas St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93759:5"/>
               <hi>God worketh all things
after the counſel of his own will.</hi> He here had his reference as St.
<hi>James</hi> had, to the great works which properly belong to God: As the
gift of his Son, and in electing ſome, ſetting a door of Mercy open to
others. And in determining the great Glory, ſhould be for the heirs of the
World to come. For the word <hi>All,</hi> in Scripture, doth not include the
whole. And as for the works of the Devil, and the evil works of Man, they do
not belong to God; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ordained Puniſhments for them after they
fell, as I have elſewhere proved. And whereas St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,
<hi>Eph.</hi> 3.8.9. <hi>That I ſhould preach among the Gentiſes the
unſearchable riches of Chriſt, and to make all men ſee what is the
fellowſhip of the Myſtery which from the beginning of the World hath been
hid in God.</hi> That is, at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the World which was laid in the
Twelve Tribes, who were laid for the beginning or Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the World to
come. They did not ſee how the <hi>Gentiles</hi> ſhould be called in, as to
become heirs with them. This great Myſtery was all a long hid in God from
them, ſo as they as little underſtood it as the Old World did: And tho' God
told <hi>Abraham,</hi> he ſhould be Father of many Nations; and the Prophets
decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the <hi>Gentiles</hi> ſhould be called in; yet it is no where
declared they ſhould be brought in by preaching the unſearchable riches of
Chriſt through the Goſpel. I have here made ſo long a digreſſion,
altho I have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more to the former Subject to ſay, the which I
could not go on with, till I had given ſome light to the true meaning of
theſe miſtaken places. That thereby I might make plain the way, for what I
have yet fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſay.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That is, we are further to conſider wherefore the Lord
ſent them forth from the Garden. Which was, <hi>Leaſt he ſhould put forth
his Hand, and take alſo of the Tree of Life. Gen.</hi> 3.22. By which words
we are to take<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93759:6"/>notice, that God doth poſitively declare,
that he did not know what Man would do, till he proved and try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, and
ſaw what was in Man. And Therefore leaſt he ſhould alſo take of the
Tree of Life, and eat and Live forever, (God having before pronounced Death for
his offence) God ſent him out of the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den. Theſe words we are to take in
the plain Letter of the Text. That God did not then know what Man would do. And
this God declaring, we are bound to believe. In as much as it is impoſſible
for God to ly. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.18. But many by not rightly apprehending theſe
forementioned places have laid the generality of the world under Eternal
Damnation, by a fore ſight in God of <hi>Adams</hi> tranſgreſſion.
Notwithſtanding God hath fully declared that when he ſaw that the
wickedneſs of Man was great upon the Earth, and that man had wholly corrupted
his way, except <hi>Noah. It repented the Lord that he had made Man on the
Earth, and it grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him at his Heart,</hi> Gen. 6.5,6,9,12. And this we are
to take in the plain Letter of the Text, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out we will blaſpheme his Holy
Name, in making the God of Truth a lyer; which is impoſſible for him to be,
<hi>Heb.</hi> 6.18. And when God promiſeth a Bleſſing, whether
conditional, or abſolute, according as he hath promiſed he will make it
good. <hi>Hath he ſaid, and ſhall he not do it? or hath he ſpoken, and
ſhall he not make it good? For God is not a man, that he ſhould lye; nor
the Son of Man, that he ſhould repent,</hi> Numb. 23.19. But upon man's
returning. God is often ſaid to Repent of the Evil he thought to do unto
them. So likewiſe of a Bleſſing, when it is promiſed on condition, and
the condition not performed, <hi>Jer.</hi> 18.8,9,10. And it was after God had
proved and tryed man, he ſaw what was in man. And ſeeing our great
High-Prieſt could not be touched with the feeling of our Infirmities, till he
took our Nature, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.15. So it was much more impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible 
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93759:6"/>that God who is of purer Eyes then to behold Iniquity with
approbation, could be cumbred with the foreſight of all the abominations and
wicked ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems of the Devil or Man before they were created, or the World
in which man offended. And the God of Truth having ſworn, that he delighteth
not in the Death of a Sinner, but rather that he ſhould return and live,
<hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.11. And how can this be true, if God had reprobated the
generality of all Mankind from all Eternity. And likewiſe God ſaith,
<hi>The Soul that ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, it ſhall dye: the Son ſhall not bear the
iniquity of the Father;</hi> Ezek. 18.20. that is when they come to be judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.
And accordingly it is ſaid, when they are judged, That every one ſhall
receive for the things done in the Body, whether it be good or bad, 2
<hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. For Chriſt will then condemn none for the Sin of
<hi>Adam</hi>'s Tranſgreſſion, the which we call Original Sin, for which
we have laid the greater part of the World un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Eternal Damnation by a
foreſight in God of <hi>Adams</hi> tranſgreſſion. And it is by the
falſe Notions which the Chriſtians have received through the miſtaken
places of Scripture, which has cauſed ſeveral to deny the Lord Chriſt to
be the Son of God; knowing that the God of Truth would not ſend his Son, and
the Servant of his Son to contradict what he had before declared: for tho' our
Faith in ſome things, may be above our Reaſon, but not contrary to
Reaſon. And tho' it is ſaid, <hi>He that planted the Ear, ſhall he not
hear? he that formed the Eye, ſhall he not ſee? Pſal.</hi> 94.7.9. This
is ſpoken only to the time after Man had a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and when they
tranſgreſſed, and thought God did not ſee. But in that God ſaid, when
Man had corrupted himſelf, that it repented him that he had made Man, and
that it grieved him at his heart. Therefore with permiſſion I ſpeak this,
it being not improbable, that if Man had fallen no otherwiſe then in
<hi>Adam</hi>'s tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93759:7"/>that then Chriſt by
taking our Nature, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in performing perfect Obedience, he might thereby
have ſatisfied Divine Juſtice, without making his Soul an Offering for Sin.
Which made the Lord Chriſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of God, that if it were poſſible
that Cup might paſs from him: But it being impoſſible that God's
juſtice could be otherwiſe ſatisfied, therefore he drank it, and God was
troubled that Man had ſo corrupted himſelf as to fall under his ſevere
Condemnation, he having no pleaſure in the Death of a Sinner, <hi>Ezek.</hi>
18.32. But many by their falſe apprehenſions, that all things were
fore-ordained before the Creation, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king no diſtinction between the great
difference that is betwixt the Creation of the World, and the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the
Foundation of the World, and by ſeveral miſtaken places. Whereby they have
made the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Love of God in the gift of his Son, only a thing
fore-determined according to the Counſel of his own Will, and that from all
Eternity. And the wonderful Love of Chriſt in laying down his Life for the
World, which Love paſſeth Knowledge, has been made a deſign in God, that
thereby ſome might be ſaved, and the reſt damned. And theſe conjectures
ſome have had of God, who is the Fountain of all Wiſdom, Love and
Juſtice, as to think that God from all Eternity, elected ſome without
Reaſon, and left the reſt to eternal Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, without having any regard
to Reaſon, Pity, or Love: But when ſuch come to be judged, they will find
that God has a reaſon for what he doth. And ſome there are that hold that
God hath two Wills, an outward Will to invite all to come and accept of
Salvation, and a ſecret Will, that only the Elect ſhall be ſaved. Which
Notions were no other then Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy againſt the God of Truth, were they
wilfully committed. And becauſe moſt of the received miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Notions
will not permit God a Reaſon for what<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93759:7"/>he doth: therefore
the foreſaid <hi>Elias, Thomas Moor,</hi> pretending to vindicate God's
juſtice more than the others, ſaith, God not making the Angels that fell,
nor Man at firſt of ability to ſtand; and therefore he ſaith, God in
Juſtice cannot puniſh Man in Hell, nor leave the Devil to damnation. And
were this true, that God did not at firſt make the Angels that fell, and Man
of ability to ſtand, I ſhould be of his mind alſo, in thinking it could
not be juſtice in God to condemn them to the Fire of Hell, for doing that
which he had before determined. But now the Prince of Darkneſs through our
miſtaken Notions, by the falſe Interpretations put upon the Scriptures, has
compleated his deſign in throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his miſcarriage and the World's upon
God, that thereby Man might be as wicked as the Devil would have them.</p>
            <p>Concerning <hi>Adam's</hi> Fall I formerly lean'd too much to the
received Notions, thinking they had been right, till by the abuſe of the
fore-mentioned Text, I made further ſearch into the Scriptures concerning it,
begging God's aſſiſtance; by which means I found we are in great
Miſtakes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>II. Shewing whom the Seeds are between whom God put
Enmity.</head>
            <p>NOw as to the Curſe the Lord laid upon the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent.
<hi>Gen</hi> 3.14,15. <hi>Thou art curſed above all Cattel, and above every
Beaſt of the Field: upon thy Belly ſhalt thou go, and Duſt ſhalt thou
eat all the days of thy Life: And I will put enmity between thee and the Woman,
and between thy Seed and her Seed; it ſhall bruiſe thy Head, and thou
ſhalt bruiſe his Heel.</hi> Now this Serpent is to be underſtood under a
twofold Head. Firſt, That this Old Serpent called the Devil, did appear in
the ſhape of a Serpent, or rather entred into a Serpent, and ſo ſpake in
the Serpent. Whoſe going was not ſo uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as we may underſtand from
the Words of the Text,<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93759:8"/>before the Curſe was laid upon him,
as after: Neither any ſuch enmity between the Woman and the Serpent. For God
made all the Creatures ſubject to <hi>Adam,</hi> and therefore then there was
no enmity between them. And after <hi>Adam</hi>'s tranſgreſſion it was
that God placed Enmity between the Seed of the Woman, and the Seed of the
Serpent: And when we would bruiſe the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, it is at his Head we
ſtrike, and he at our Heels. And that there was a real Serpent, it doth
further ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, in that he was to go upon his Belly all the days of his Life;
which accordingly he doth. But in that the Scriptures are of more then a
private Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20. And therefore this Scrrpture
hath its chief tendency to the Old Serpent, called the Devil, whom Chriſt the
Seed of the Woman ſhould bruiſe. And likewiſe between the Seed of the
Woman, and the Seed of the Old Serpent, God hath alſo put En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity. But who
this Seed of the Old Serpent was, or is, is here to be conſidered. Whereas
God ſaid, <hi>I will put Enmity between the Seed of the Woman, and the Seed
of the Serpent,</hi> Gen. 3.15. And the Serpent has no other Seed but what does
adhere to him; and then none had adhered to him to give themſelves to his
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe but the Angels whom he drew off with him when he revolted; and
therefore he is called <hi>Belzebub</hi> the Prince of the Devils,
<hi>Matth.</hi> 12.24. And it was for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and his Angels that Hell-Fire
was prepared, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.41. And it was between this Seed of the
Serpent, and the Seed of the Woman that God did then put Enmity; for the Prince
of <hi>darkneſs</hi> then had no other Seed but the Angels that fell: For
when <hi>Eve</hi> bore <hi>Cain,</hi> ſhe ſaid, <hi>I have gotten a Man
from the Lord:</hi> And therefore then he was not the Seed of the Serpent. And
for <hi>Cain</hi>'s firſt Offence, God did not caſt him out of his
preſence, but ſaid, <hi>If thou doſt well, ſhalt thou not be excepted?
but if thou doſt Evil, Sin lieth at thy Door,</hi> Gen. 4.7. But he by 
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93759:8"/>adding Sin to Sin, thereby became of that Evil One for which
God caſt him out of his preſence. So the Seed of <hi>Seth,</hi> whilſt
they ſerved God, were called the Sons of God. But when they had corrupted
their Way, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the earth was filled with Violence they were alike cut off
together. And ſo <hi>Iſrael,</hi> of whom God ſaid, <hi>I had planted
thee a noble Vine, a holy and a right Seed,</hi> Jer. 2.21. God having before
proved and tryed <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 22.16,17,18. of whom <hi>Iſrael</hi>
ſprang, and had they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in the ſteps of <hi>Abraham,</hi> they
would have remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Bleſſed: but they turned into the degenerate plant of
a ſtrange Vine, <hi>ver.</hi> 21. For when they forſook the holy
Commandment, and did ſtrain at a Gnat and ſwallow a Camel, <hi>Mat.</hi>
23.23,24. For they wanted Faith in the Belief of the Writings of the Prophets,
as to think that the threatned Judgments from God by them would fall on them,
if they were diſobedient to the weightier matters of the Law; and therefore
Chriſt ſaid in the Parable, <hi>If they will not believe</hi> Moſes
<hi>and the Prophets,</hi> (as to be warned by them) <hi>neither will they
believe, though one roſe from the Dead,</hi> Luke 16.29,30,31. And alſo
Chriſt ſaith, <hi>For had they believed</hi> Moſes, <hi>they would have
believed me, for he wrote of me,</hi> John 5.46. For had they lived
blameleſly, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.6. according to the rule God had given,
<hi>Iſrael</hi> had never been left to Blindneſs. And it was better for
them to whom Chriſt ſpake in Parables and dark Sentences, and did not his
mighty Works amongſt them, nor ſuffered his Diſciples to declare them,
that ſo they might be left to Blindneſs, then thoſe where he did his
mighty Works which never Man did, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.24,35. there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to convince
them: Yet they would wilfully ſet themſelves in oppoſition; therefore
Chriſt ſaid, <hi>It ſhould be more tolerable for</hi> Tire <hi>and</hi>
Sidon, <hi>and</hi> Sodom, <hi>in the Day of Judgment then for ſuch,</hi>
Mat. 11.22,23,24. Deut. 32.5. And whereas ſome of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were 
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93759:9"/>elected, and to others of them, a door of mercy ſet open,
but the greater number of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were left to Blindneſs. And St.
<hi>Peter</hi> ſaith of Iſrael, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.47. <hi>The Lord added to
the Church daily ſuch as ſhould be ſaved.</hi> Becauſe ſome of them
were likewiſe ſaved by afore-appointment, whilſt it happened that for Sin
the major part of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were left to Blindneſs, <hi>Rom.</hi>
11.25. And the major part in Scripture is often called as the whole, or all;
but it was the major part was left to blindneſs. So likewiſe the
<hi>Gentiles</hi> that were fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choſen, and who firſt believed,
<hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.12. were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by God, <hi>that the World through them
might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve.</hi> John 17.21. For there was a particular and a general
Calling by the Goſpel, by which general Call the Nations embraced the Faith,
and became the Seed of <hi>Abraham:</hi> But when they came to have no Love to
the Truth, but took pleaſure in Unrighteouſneſs, God gave them up to
ſtrong Deluſions to believe Lyes, that they might be damned, 2
<hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.10,11,12. Here are two things lays People under Damnation;
<hi>firſt,</hi> In having no Love to the Truth. 2dly, In taking plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
in Unrighteouſneſs. And thoſe that have no Love to the Truth, are not
only thoſe that laid the World in Darkneſs, but alſo all thoſe that doe
wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully oppoſe the Truth, thereby to keep the World in Darkneſs.</p>
            <p>For all ſuch as would rather let God be diſhonoured, and the
Bible made to contradict it ſelf, and his People deſtroyed for lack of
Knowledge, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 4.6. rather than themſelves be found in a
miſtake. Such may eaſily conclude what will be their portion.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:93759:9"/>
            <head>III. How the Spirit of Chriſt muſt be in us, if we are
his.</head>
            <p>ROmans 8.1. <hi>There is therefore no Condemnation to them that
are in Chriſt Jeſus, who walk not after the Fleſh, but after the
Spirit.</hi> That is, ſuch as walk after the Spirit, are in Chriſt Jeſus.
For ſuch are ſaid, not to be in the Fleſh, but in the Spirit, if ſo be
the Spirit of God dwell in them. <hi>Now if any man have not the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of
Chriſt, he is none of his,</hi> verſ. 9. Now there was a twofold Indwelling
of God in the firſt Churches by his Spirit. That is, there was firſt a
complying frame of Spirit to the Will of God, ſo as not to walk after the
Will of the Fleſh, but after the Spirit; which was in a holy Converſation,
without which no Man ſhall ſee the Lord, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14. For if we
have not thus the Spirit of Chriſt, we are none of his; for it is required
that the ſame Mind be in us as was in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.5.
Therefore it is not the Seed after the Fleſh to whom the Promiſe belongs,
which live after the Will of the Fleſh and of the Mind, whether of the
natural or the adopted Seed of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> they are not the Seed to whom
the Promiſe is made; but the Seed in Chriſt, and <hi>Iſaac,</hi> both of
<hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile,</hi> which walk not after the Fleſh, but after
the Spirit, ſo as to have their Wills brought into ſubjection unto the Will
of God, are the Seed to whom the Promiſe belongs. For <hi>to be carnally
minded is Death; but to be ſpiritually minded is Life and Peace,</hi> verſ.
6. For the Kingdom of God and Chriſt muſt be within us, <hi>Luke</hi>
17.21. if we are his. For Chriſt muſt have the ruling Power in the Heart:
And God alſo ſaith, <hi>Give me thy Heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And when we give to God and Chriſt the ruling Power in our
Heart, then is his Kingdom within us. And if <hi>Chriſt be in us, the body is
dead becauſe of Sin, but the Spirit is Life becauſe of
Righteouſneſs,</hi> verſ. 10. Thus<pb n="18" facs="tcp:93759:10"/>the true Believer
is dead to the World, that he may live to God. And this ruling power Chriſt
had in the hearts of his Diſciples, before he gave them the Holy Ghoſt. And
likewiſe, all that did receive the Holy Ghoſt to be in them, for the
confirmation of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, Chriſt had firſt the ruling power in their
hearts, and they yielded to him to be his Servants, and then were they
Baptized; and thus they were prepared be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they could receive the Holy
Ghoſt to be in them, by which they were then glorified, and had power to
ſpeak with Tongues and work Miracles, and Propheſy, and underſtand
Propheſies, for the Spirit was to teach them all things, <hi>John</hi> 14.26.
And ſo by all it was then known who were the Elect: And theſe were thoſe
whom God made to differ, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7. But ſome through neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence
and heedleſneſs, the Prince of Darkneſs makes to differ, they following
his dictates and ſo corrupt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
way; and when they have accuſtomed themſelve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> do evil,
then it is they cannot learn to do well. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> ſome make themſelves to differ by taking heed to their Ways,
according to the Word of God. And ſo by conſidering their ways, they become
wiſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. For
God hath promiſed to bleſs ſuch endeavours, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.6. For the
common drawings of God, are the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitations of his Word, and the good motions
of his Spirit. But the fore-mentioned were choſen according to the Counſel
of the Will of God; by the which Will, they were ſanctified, <hi>Heb.</hi>
10.10. And recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Holy Ghoſt to be in them. And Chriſt ſaid,
<hi>the World could not receive the Holy Ghoſt, becauſe they knew him
not,</hi> John 14.17. For the World then lay in Wickedneſs, and therefore
they could not then receive him, becauſe they knew him not, and were not
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the receiving of him. 2dly, God did not intend to give the World
the Holy Ghoſt to be in them, but to be with all ſuch as will keep his Way.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93759:10"/>And therefore Chriſt prayed for his Diſciples, and
firſt Churches which believed on him through the Word
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Diſciples, as he did not for
the World, <hi>but that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> World
through them might believe,</hi> that God had ſent him, <hi>John</hi> 17.21.
And therein he prayed for the World; and by the evident Witneſs of the Holy
Ghoſt in them, the World did believe, and the Nations embraced the Faith by
laying hold of the offered Mercy in the common Salvation. And Chriſt did but
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe the Remnant, which were his Father's Sheep be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and given to
him, that he would be with them to the end of the World; and that <hi>he would
ſend them another Comforter, which ſhould abide with them for ever,</hi>
John 14.16. But he doth not ſay <hi>In them</hi> for ever, And he will be
with all while they keep the Way. But the Apoſtle knowing that the Holy
Ghoſt would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> remain in their
ſucceeding Generations in this time;
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>efore he ſaith, <hi>Propheſie
ſhould fail, and Tongues they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ould ceaſe, and Knowledge it ſhould vaniſh away,</hi> 1
<hi>Cor.</hi> 13.8. Which came to paſs when the Nations came to have no Love
to the Truth, but took pleaſure in Unrighteouſneſs. Then <hi>God gave
them up to ſtrong de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ſions,
that they ſhould believe Lyes,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.10,11,12.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he did <hi>Iſrael</hi> for
Sin to blindneſs of Mind: But Love and Charity among the Faithful was ever to
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main, as Love to God in their obedient walking ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to knowledge, and
Charity to their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. <hi>For Faith, Hope, and Charity,</hi> were the
Graces that would abide, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.13. with them that will be
faithful. And the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>The time would come, when they would
not endure found Doctrine; but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their own Luſt ſhall turn away their
Ears from the Truth.</hi> For the generality of the World choſe to
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves falſe Teachers, before God gave them up to deluſions, 2
<hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3. For a Believer is no longer a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever, than a Righteous
Man is a Righteous Man in <pb n="20" facs="tcp:93759:11"/>the day that he wilfully commits
Iniquity, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.12. But they which live holily, thereby bring forth
Fruit to the Spirit. But the Eternal Life that Chriſt gave to his Sheep,
which were his Father's before, was given to their Perſons and Poſterity,
and to every Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever while they continue in Believing, Salvation is to be
had, according to his Word, in the way of their Obedience. <hi>For every Tree
which bringeth not forth good Fruit is hewn down and caſt into the Fire,</hi>
Mat. 3.10. And it is a meer Stratagem of the Prince of Darkneſs, in
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading any Man God will not puniſh according to his Word; that was the
way he beguiled <hi>Ewe,</hi> and ſo he doth the generality of Mankind.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>IV. A Twofold Indwelling of Chriſt by his Spirit in the
firſt Churches.</head>
            <p>AND whereas St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.11. <hi>But
if the Spirit of him that raiſed up Jeſus from the Dead dwell in you; he
that raiſed up Chriſt from the Dead,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> alſo quicken your mortal
Bodies by his Spirit that dwelleth in you.</hi> Here the Apoſtle writes to
the elect Church among the <hi>Romans,</hi> who were then called and
juſtified, and glorified, by receiving the Holy Ghoſt to be in them, 1
<hi>Pet.</hi> 1.11,12. But theſe had not the Promiſe from Chriſt, that
none ſhould pluck them out of his Hand: That Promiſe did appertain to the
Diſciples, which were of that Remnant choſen from among <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,
John</hi> 10.27,28,29. Of which Remnant were the Elect that ſhould never be
deceived by the Beaſt nor falſe Prophet: And they are the Foundation which
ſtandeth ſure. But the forementioned, which were the Elect among the
<hi>Gentiles,</hi> were cleared from their paſt Sins, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25. by
the Imputation of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs; and therefore he ſaith,
<hi>Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of God's elect? It is God that
ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth,</hi> Rom. 8.33. But after they were thus cleared 
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:93759:11"/>from their paſt Sins, they were to walk in newneſs of
Life, and ſo are all. And therefore when he found the Elect to walk
diſorderly, and were guilty of Sin, he
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not ſparing to charge them
with it, and reprove them for it, like as he did others, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1. But
he ſaith, <hi>verſ.</hi> 35, 36, 37, 38, 39. He was perſwaded that
<hi>neither tribulation, nor diſtreſs, nor death, nor life, nor height, nor
depth, nor any other Creature ſhall be able to ſeparate them from the Love
of God which is in Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> But in the forementioned Verſes, he
mentions not Sin; knowing that wilful Sin will ſeperate them from God;
there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtle ſaith, verſ. 11. <hi>And if the Spirit of him that
raiſed Jeſus from the Dead, dwell in you;</hi> that is, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue or remain
in them. And accordingly he ſaith to the Elect Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi>
chap. 11.3. Fearing <hi>leſt the Serpent ſhould beguile them as he
beguiled</hi> Eve. And then their mortal Bodies will not be quickned again
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his Spirit being in them; but
if they did not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ve the Holy
Ghoſt, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.13. thereby to cauſe him to withdraw, then the
ſame Spirit would raiſe up their mortal Bodies to have a part in the
firſt Reſurrection, and to partake of the glory
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen the Lord again comes,
<hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4,5. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.7.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it is alſo by the ſame
Spirit and Power of God that all that has done either good or bad, ſhall be
raiſed up at the laſt Judgment: For Chriſt ſaith, <hi>All that are in
the Graves, ſhall hear his Voice, and ſhall come forth, they that have done
good, to the Reſurrection of Life, and they that have done evil, unto the
Reſurrection of Danna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> John 5.28,29. But all that remain faithful
to the Lord Jeſus, longing for his appearing: Though they have not the Holy
Ghoſt in them, but with them, they ſhall likewiſe have their part in the
firſt Reſurrection, and receive the Crown of Righteouſneſs in that day,
2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. ver. 8. But the Lord ſpeaking of the firſt
Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, mentions it very darkly, <hi>John</hi> 5.25. becauſe he 
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93759:12"/>ſpake to the <hi>Jews</hi> that were to be left to
blindneſs, ſo as <hi>ſeeing they might ſee, and not perceive; and
hearing they might hear, and not underſtand,</hi> Iſa. 6.9,10. And
like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it is ſaid, the Lord <hi>ſpake to them in Parables, and without
a Parable ſpake he not unto them,</hi> Mat. 13.34. And therefore the Lord
alſo ſpeaks to them darkly about the firſt Reſurrection, verſ. 25.
<hi>Verily, verily, I ſay unto you, the Hour is coming, and now is, when the
Dead ſhall hear the Voice of the Son of God, and they that hear ſhall
live.</hi> Theſe words may have a twofold ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency in having ſome
reference to the firſt Churches which had the peculiar calling, and thereby
brought in, which was the Hour that then was; but whereas the Lord ſaith
<hi>the Hour is coming,</hi> that of certain is the time when he again ſhould
come; at which time the dead Bodies of the Saints ſhall hear the Voice of the
Son of God and live: And alſo then dead <hi>Iſrael</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> both ſee him, and hear his
Voice and live. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> theſe
words had their chief reference to the time
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Judgment, Power, and Honour is
given to the Son, is evident by the 22, 23. Verſes. But according as the
Evangeliſt ſaith, So ſpake the Lord to them <hi>in Parable,</hi> that
they did not underſtand it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.34. And th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> it is the Saints that riſe in the firſt
Reſurrection; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all that have
done good, ſhall afterwards ariſe to the Reſurrection of Life. And
<hi>Iſrael,</hi> when judged, will not be condemned for that they ignorantly
committed againſt Chriſt, for he prayed for them, <hi>Luke</hi> 23.24.
Bleſſed be the great and glorious God, who hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled a weak Worm to
vindicate his Juſtice to the praiſe of his Name, and the comfort of his
Creatures. In that it is now made clearly appear, the Judge of all the World
will do right; who publiſheth his Praiſe by the weak things of this World,
that thereby all the Glory may be attributed to himſelf, who is God
bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for ever and ever.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:93759:12"/>
            <head>V. Concerning Election.</head>
            <p>ELection doth not always ſecure the Elect from fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling off; but
by God's electing ſome, it was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to accompliſh the Counſel of the
Will of God, as to what he had before determined: And therefore ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly
<hi>he gave to one five Talents, to the other two, and to the other but one,
but every Man had given him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his ability,</hi> Matth. 25.15. And
each having given them according to their ability, that they might according to
their day be capable to ſtand: But them that was of the Remnant of
<hi>Iſrael,</hi> of whom the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples were, they did not only ſtand by
their Election, but by a Promiſe from the Lord, That <hi>none ſhould
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ck them out of his Hand,</hi> John
10.28,29. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ikewiſe both the
Diſciples and firſt Churches received
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Holy Ghoſt to be in them,
whereby they were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ed to God by one
Spirit, and ſo beame a Light to the World; and thereby the Prayer of Chriſt
was fulfilled, in that the World through them might believe that God had ſent
him, <hi>John</hi> 17.21. Which accordingly
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>llowed, for the Nations embraced
the Faith, and ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>came the Seed
of <hi>Abraham.</hi> But the Elect were to Withſtand all the Fury of the
Adverſaries, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had the more Talents given them; for on them was
ſhed forth the Holy Ghoſt abundantly, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.6. But if they did
<hi>grieve the Holy Spirit of God, whereby they were Sealed to the Day of
Redemption,</hi> Eph. 4.30. For if they <hi>ſinned wilfully after they had
received the knowledge of the Truth, there remaineth no more Sacrifice for Sin,
but a certain fearful looking for of Judgment, and fiery Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi>
Heb. 10.26, 27. (But all that have a true Heart ſeparate from an evil
Conſcience, may draw nigh to God in full aſſurance of Faith, that they
ſhall find acceptance through the Blood of the Lord Jeſus, and 
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93759:13"/>they in a more ſpecial manner who were fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choſen to
it, verſ. 22.) Now theſe having the greater Light, if they fell away, fell
under the greater Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation. And that ſome of the Elect did fall away,
that was not ſecured by a Promiſe from Chriſt, is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain by what St.
<hi>John</hi> ſaith, That <hi>if they had been of them, they would have
continued with them,</hi> 1 John 2.19. Therefore they were not of that Remnant,
but it is clear they were of the Elect, becauſe the Elect then were known by
their Speaking with Tongues, and by the Gifts that were given them, by which
God made them to differ; for had they not received thoſe Gifts, it would have
been known they had been none of the Elect before they went out from them; but
by their going out from them, they knew that they were not of them to whom the
Promiſe was made: Which were the Remnant; and as St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith,
<hi>It is better not to know the Way of Righteouſneſs, than after they have
known it, to turn from the Holy Commandment,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.18,21. And alſo of
others it is ſaid, <hi>they made Shipwrack of Faith and a good
Conſcience,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.19. For tho' the elect were fore-choſen without
their willing or run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, yet when they were brought into the knowledge of the
Truth, they were to make their Calling and Election ſure by improving their
Talents; for there was a part for them to do, before they could receive their
Eternal Inheritance, unleſs they were immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly removed by Death; And
therefore ſaved by Faith, and good Works, <hi>James</hi> 2.24. So we ſee,
none ſtood ſecurely, only by their Election; but the generality of the
firſt Churches ſtanding, the major part in Scripture is reckoned for the
whole. And the Servant to whom the one Talent was given, was the world, and the
Teachers of the World; which after the Goſpel was received and
eſtabliſhed, the Word was then the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, which had they according to
their ability impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,<pb n="25" facs="tcp:93759:13"/>they had thereby been capable to
ſtand, God ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving promiſed to all, whilſt they kept to the way, his
aſſiſtance. But the evil Servant, the Man of Sin got Ground, who were the
Teachers in the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, which hid the Talent of the Word, and
would not improve it themſelves, nor ſuffer the Truth to be known among the
People, among whom it might have been improved, according to the ſimilitude
the Lord put forth concerning the Money-Changers, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.15,27. And
likewiſe them that will oppoſe and ſmother the Truth, will not be counted
guiltleſs, when the Lord Chriſt ſhall come. And it is the He-Goats that
have eaten the good Paſtures, and trodden down the reſidue, and fouled the
deep Waters, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.17,18. By the falſe Interpretations that have
been put upon the Word, ſo as the Flock of Chriſt eat that which they have
trodden, and drank that which they have fouled with their Feet,
<hi>verſ.</hi> 19. For which when the Lord comes, his ſevere Judgments will
fall on them, and then will the Lord feed his Sheep himſelf; ſo as then his
Sheep ſhall be no more a Prey, as in the 22, 23, 24. Verſes; For this is
ſpoken of the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar time, in which the Lord vvill come to Judge and
Reign. And Man in this time was truſted with the Word for his Poſterity, as
<hi>Adam</hi> was truſted with E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Life for his Poſterity. Therefore
the Lord alike laid his Commands, that <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould not eat of the
Tree, nor we add or diminiſh either to or from his Word, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.2.
<hi>Rev.</hi> 22.18. The which Word we are to hold faſt till the Lord comes,
<hi>Rev.</hi> 2.25. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.2,3. But theſe forementioned. Teachers
that hid the Word, would not ſo much as ſuffer or permit any Woman to look
into it. But when Man acts contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to God, God acts contrary to Man. The Lord
awaken all the Miniſters that truly fear his Name of all parties, that by
their acknowledging and owning<pb n="26" facs="tcp:93759:14"/>the whole Truth, they thereby
may clear them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the Blood of all Men, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.26,27. as
they may not be reckoned with the Goats, And that by them Millions of Souls may
be brought out of their miſtaken Notions; and that they themſelves for ſo
doing, may ſhine as the Stars; but them that will take advantage of the
People's Ignorance, that thereby they may keep them in Miſtakes and
Darkneſs, it will be a wofull day to them.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>VI. Concerning Chriſt and the Elect Angels.</head>
            <p>NOw Chriſt is ſaid to be God's <hi>Elect in whom his Soul
delighteth,</hi> Iſa. 42.1. But he was not Elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed becauſe there was any
danger of his falling; but he was elected according to the purpoſe of God:
That by him might be made good the promiſe God made to our firſt Parents.
That by the Seed of the Woman, the Serpent's Head ſhould be bruiſed. And as
for the elect Angels St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of, it doth not appear, that
they were elected, becauſe the fallen Angels had left their own Habitation,
<hi>Jude</hi> verſ. 6. And therefore God would afterward ſecure the reſt
of the Angels by electing them; but rather that God did elect them for a
purpoſe he had determined. For the terrible Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God reſting upon
the Angels that fell, who are reſerved in everlaſting Chains under
Darkneſs, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Judgment of the great Day. Which thing is known to all
the holy Angels, and ſo a warning to keep them from falling. And the reaſon
of <hi>Lucifer</hi>'s Fall, was not becauſe he was not ſo much in the
favour of God as the other Angels, for he was one of the greateſt, if not the
greateſt Angel of God: And thro' the greatneſs of the power which God had
given him, he ſet himſelf in oppoſition to God, and ſo drew off others
of the Angels with him in that great Rebellion. But if Man had not ſinned,
Chriſt had not ſuffered;<pb n="27" facs="tcp:93759:14"/>and Chriſt laid down his Life
for the World. But I do not here deny, but am ready to believe that all the
Heavenly Hoſt that is now remaining in Heaven, as Arch-Angels, Angels,
Cherubims, and Seraphims, might have a Promiſe from God after the Fall, that
their ſtanding ſhould be ſecured to them through Chriſt. But in that
St. <hi>Paul</hi> mentions the elect Angels, from thoſe words is rather to be
underſtood, that they were Angels whom God had made choice of to aſſiſt
and aid Man: And according to this Chriſt ſaith of Children, <hi>That in
Heaven their Angels do always behold the face of his Father,</hi> Mat. 18.10.
So likewiſe the Diſciples told the Damſel, when ſhe affirmed that
<hi>Peter</hi> knocked at the door, that <hi>it was his Angel,</hi> Acts 12.15.
From theſe Texts it is clear, that there are ſome Angels that in particular
are concerned with us, and were elected and choſen for that purpoſe; and
ſo they being more near our Perſons man the other Angels, and thereby know
our Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions, and therefore more probable the Apoſtle gave
<hi>Timothy</hi> his charge before God, and Chriſt, and the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect Angels, 1.
<hi>Tim.</hi> 5.21. Which Angels being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed concerning them, could
likewiſe bear witneſs of this his Charge: And in the whole Book of God
there is no mention made of elect Angels but in this place, and therefore it
doth appear to be as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>And after the Creation, <hi>God ſaw every thing that he had
made, and it was very good, Gen.</hi> 1.31. as to what he had then made,
nothing had defiled it ſelf. Therefore when God made the Stars they were then
all very good and God made the Lights for Signs, and for Seaſons, and for
Days, and for Years, <hi>vers</hi> 14. And they being in the Creation by God
made very good, therefore they were not made of God to influence Man to
Iniquity; But as the Prince of Darkneſs drew off part of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and Man,
ſo likewiſe he drew off part of the Stars alſo, by which he doth
influence Man to Iniquity; for<pb n="28" facs="tcp:93759:15"/>by his drawing the Stars, is
not only meant the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Word, which he hath drawn after him,
<hi>Rev.</hi> 12.4. <hi>Jude</hi> verſ. 13. but the real Stars alſo; but
with care and Prayer, their evil Influences may, and is to be withſtood.
Likewiſe, the Tree of Knowledge of Good and Evil, was of God made good; but
by the knowledge of Evil, and liking it, he became a Devil; For the Tree of
Knowledge of Good and Evil, was the Devil, or the repreſentative of the
Devil; as the Tree of Life was the repreſentative of Chriſt, as by the Word
I have clearly proved in my Book of the <hi>Explanation of the New
Teſtament,</hi> and <hi>the Three Worlds;</hi> but God forewarned them of
this evil Root: and had they firſt taken of the Tree of Life, they might have
eaten and lived for ever; but this evil root in time to come will be ſealed
up, and then will the evil Stars fall down into Blackneſs and Darkneſs for
ever, <hi>Jude</hi> verſ. 13. And the Elect that will be gathered in from the
Four Winds, after the Lord comes, they will be <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as I have
fully proved in my forementioned Book: But their ſtanding will not be
ſecured from their Election, but by God's then eſtabliſhing the
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed New Everlaſting Covenant with them; in which the Saints and true
Believers will then be inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as Heirs with them to the ſame Promiſe.
And there is of the <hi>Heathen</hi> fore-appointed then to be called in, but
not being ſecured by the Everlaſting Covenant, part of their Poſterity
will afterward be inſnared again, as I have made appear in the foreſaid
Book. As for thoſe that talk of a Covenant of Grace from all Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,
therein they know not what they ſay, nor what they affirm: But the
forementioned miſtaken places treated in the 6, 7, 8, and 9 pages, has
occaſioned theſe ſo great and dangerous Errors; for the Covenant that
will make the Inheritors of it eternally bleſſed, is ſtill but the
Covenant of Promiſe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.29. <hi>And if ye are<pb n="29" facs="tcp:93759:15"/>Chriſt's, then are ye</hi> Abraham's <hi>Seed, and Heirs accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to the Promiſe:</hi> which Promiſe was the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the New
Everlaſting Covenant with <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed together,
<hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7,8,9. The which the Remnant, and firſt Churches were
choſen to be Heirs to; and a Door of Mercy ſet open to others, that now
they might freely come by the Call of the Goſpel. And whereas the Apoſtle
after he had rehearſed the promiſed Covenant, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. The which
they were fore-choſen to be Heirs to; ſaith of the Old Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, That
<hi>it was ready to vaniſh away,</hi> verſ. 13. And in the 9th Chap.
expoſtulating about the Ceremonial Law, ſhewing they were but <hi>Shadows
of good things to come,</hi> ver. 11. And therefore ſaith, <hi>That they
which are called, might receive the Promiſe of the Eternal Inheritance,</hi>
ver. 16. The which was the Promiſe of the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Covenant. And in
ver. 27. he ſaith, <hi>It is appointed for Men once to die, and after this to
come to Judgment.</hi> For they muſt riſe again, and come to Judgment,
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this Covenant will be eſtabliſhed, And then <hi>to them that look
for him, ſhall he appear the ſecond time without Sin unto Salvation,</hi>
Heb. 9.28 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. For they are to <hi>have their part in the
firſt Reſurrection,</hi> Rev. 20.6. the which will be at the time of
Reſtitution, for then will the Lord redeem <hi>Iſrael</hi> from all their
Sins, and eſtabliſh his Everlaſting Covenant; and then it is <hi>Iſrael
will be all Righteous, and inherit the Land for ever, Iſa.</hi> 60.21. For
there is to be another time according to the former time, in which it ſhall
be ſaid of <hi>Jacob</hi> and of <hi>Iſrael, What hath God wrought?</hi>
Num. 23.23. And then it is God will behold no Iniquity in <hi>Jacob,</hi> when
he hath purged all Iniquity from them; for then he will for ever perfect them
that are ſanctified, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.14. For God, and Chriſt, the
Prophets, and Apoſtles, mention things which are to come, as if they were
al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready paſt or preſent. Theſe things were eaſie to be 
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:93759:16"/>underſtood by them that had been well inſtructed
therein, as all they were, to whom the Apoſtles writ their Epiſtels; but
unto us that come ſo many Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions after the knowledge of theſe things,
were loſt by the Nations falling into Popery, by which they were deprived of
the Scriptures for ſeveral hundred Years, and ſo they loſt the true
meaning of them; but in that any of us have been ſo miſtaken as to think
the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant is now made with us, is moſt amazing, ſeeing by
that Covenant they were all to be taught of God; ſo as they ſhould no more
teach every Man his Neighbour, and his Brother, when we all know in this time,
the Goſpel was eſtabliſht to be taught, and that all ſince have been
taught either right or wrong; but had we only thought this Covenant had been
made with them who were the firſt Publiſhers of the Goſpel, and were then
taught of God, and had the evident witneſs of the Holy Ghoſt in them, and
the mighty power of God going along with them, this would have been of no great
damage to us, but to think that we are now in the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this
promiſed Covenant is a ſtrange deluſion, and of moſt dangerous
conſequence, for thereby ſome have thought they might fall foully, but not
finally, and thereby ſome have made themſelves eternally miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
which had they not known thoſe notions they might have been bleſſed; but
when this Covenant is eſtabliſhed they will not Sin; but in this time,
<hi>Whoſoever ſays he is without ſin is a Lyer, and the Truth is not in
him.</hi> 1 Joh. 1.8.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>VII. Concerning the Light that lighteth every Man.</head>
            <p>WHereas it is ſaid <hi>John</hi> 1.9. <hi>That Chriſt is the
true Light that lighteth every Man that cometh into the World.</hi> Now in that
Chriſt is ſaid to lighten every Man, is becauſe Chriſt is ſaid to be
Wiſdom. <hi>Pro.</hi> 8.22.23.30,31. <hi>In whom are hid all the Treaſures
of Wiſdom<pb n="31" facs="tcp:93759:16"/>and Knowledge,</hi> Col. 2.3. And ſo far as
Men retain right Reaſon and Conſcience, to all ſuch Chriſt is a Light;
for right Reaſon and Conſcience is the Light which God hath ſet up in the
Soul, which if followed, God will never leave ſuch to eternal Death, tho' it
is only the Believer is promiſed eternal Life, and to have their part in the
firſt Reſurrection, for <hi>St. Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Thoſe that know
not the Law; yet do by Nature the things contained in the Law, their
Conſcience will excuſe them.</hi> Rom. 2.14,15. According to which Chriſt
ſaith, <hi>If thine Eye be ſingle thy whole Body is full of Light, but if
thy Eye be evil, then the whole Body is full of Darkneſs.</hi> That is, if
our Eye be ſingle we are then impartial to our ſelves, and judge our
ſelves according to right Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Conſcience, ſuch have Light; but
if thine Eye be evil, that is blind to thy ſelf, ſuch are full of
Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and then how great is that Darkneſs? <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.22,23, for
that leads to utter Darkneſs. But for ſome there is a Redemption in the
World to come, for all that dyed in <hi>Adams</hi> Tranſgreſſion will be
cleared from Original Sin by Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.22. and ſo a
Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for all Children in time to come; <hi>For then the Son ſhall not
bear the Iniquity of the Father, neither ſhall the Father bear the Iniquity
of the Son, the Soul that ſinneth it ſhall Dye,</hi> Ezek. 18.20. But in
this time it is only the Children of the Believer is Holy, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi>
7.14. before they have committed actual Sin, and the Believer is he that
believes Salvation is to be had according to the words of Chriſt; but at
Judgment there is none Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned but for the Deeds done in the Body. 1
<hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. and then all Children will be cleared; and likewiſe all
them unto whom God hath promiſed Mercy, will then accordingly find Mercy, as
the Meek, the Merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, &amp;c. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. and all that order their
converſation aright, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.23. and the Ignorant ſhall be
beaten with fewer Stripes than thoſe that wilfully offend.<pb n="32" facs="tcp:93759:17"/>
               <hi>Luke</hi> 12.47. And whereas it is ſaid, <hi>He that hath the
Son hath Life, and he that hath not the Son of God hath not Life.</hi> 1 John
5.12. Theſe Words do no ways exclude a Redemption by Chriſt for ſome in
the World to come, or Reſtoration; but for ſome Sin there is neither
for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs in this World, nor in the World to come. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.32. 1
<hi>Joh.</hi> 5.16. But whereas it is ſaid, Where the Tree falleth there it
lieth, thereby it ſhews that after Death we can no ways help our ſelves, as
we may now by Repentance and Amendment of Life; but all that go into the Pit,
muſt there ſtay till they are brought to Judgment to receive their Sentence
of releaſe or final Condemnation; but the coming of the Lord, the rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
of the Saints, the judgment of this World, and the reſtoration of
<hi>Iſrael,</hi> will be many Ages before the laſt Judgment, when the Sea,
Hell and Death deliver up their Dead. <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.12. In which God hath
ſecret places for Souls which we know not of, for all that go not to Heaven,
do not go to the Fire of Hell, for what the Lord ſpeaks by the Law and
Goſpel, is but to them that are under it (as I have proved) and for them that
are under the greater <hi>light,</hi> they will fall under the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
Condemnation; but whereas the Prophet prays, <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.25. <hi>Pour out
thy Fury upon the Heathen that know thee not, and upon the Families that call
not on thy Name, for they have eaten up</hi> Jacob, <hi>and devoured him, and
conſumed him, and have made his Habitation Deſolate.</hi> The Prophets
Petition here is only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe Heathens that devoured <hi>Jacob,</hi>
and laid waſt his Dwelling Place. The ſame alſo is ſaid upon their like
Cruelties in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 79.6,7. And whereas the Apoſtle ſaith, The
Lord will come to take Vengance on them that know not God, and that obey not
the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.8. And thoſe
are they that know not God, that believe he will not Reward and Puniſh
according to his Word.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:93759:17"/>
            <head>VIII. Concerning the drawings of God, as to when and upon what
account Chriſt then thus Spake.</head>
            <p>NOW whereas the Lord ſaith, <hi>No Man can come to him except
the Father draw him,</hi> John 6.44. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the Lord ſaith in
<hi>verſ.</hi> 65. <hi>No Man can come unto me, except it were given unto him
of my Father.</hi> The Lord Chriſt hath here his reference to the then time,
in which he appeared as a mean Perſon, which in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is termed the form
of a Servant, and thoſe that were then firſt called in, had the more
immediate draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of God; and the Words of the Lord here had their tendency
to the Remnant, with the reſt of the Elect that were given him of his Father,
unto whom the Holy Ghoſt was afterwards given to be in them. And therefore
the Lord ſaith in the 45. <hi>verſ. It is written in the Prophets, and they
ſhall be all taught of God.</hi> The Lord here having his reference to the
time that the Holy Ghoſt ſhould be given, for the eſtabliſhing of the
Goſpel, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.3,4. and as an earneſt of their Inheritance in time
to come, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 1.14. And whereas the Lord ſaith, <hi>Every Man that
hath learned of the Father cometh unto me.</hi> Whether the Lord in theſe
Words meaneth only the Sheep, that were his Fathers before, and given to him,
or all them of <hi>Iſrael</hi> who then lived according to the rule of Gods
Word, for of ſuch it may be ſaid they were taught of God, in that they were
guided by his Precept, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all that fear his Name in <hi>Iſrael</hi>
was the Word of this Salvation ſent, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.26. But the Lord
ſeems rather here to have his peculiar reference to them that was then given
him by his Father; but the reaſon the Lord ſpeaketh thus myſtically to
them, was becauſe the Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude had ſeen the great Miracle that he did, in
feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Five Thouſand with Four Loaves and Two Fiſhes. Upon which the
Multitude thought to have taken him by force, and to have made him a King; but
the Lord<pb n="34" facs="tcp:93759:18"/>knowing their thoughts went privatly from them, and
the Multitude ſeeking after the Lord, which when they again had found him, he
then ſpake ſo myſtically unto them, that they could not underſtand him,
and therefore they ſaid they were hard ſayings, who could bear them? and
from that time many of the Diſciples went back, and ſo the Lord brake their
deſign of mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him a King, for his time to Reign was not then; but theſe
very Perſons that did not then wilfully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from him, but went away
becauſe they could not then underſtand his ſayings, Chriſt ſaid unto
them in the 27. verſ. <hi>Labour not for the Meat which periſheth, but for
that Meat which endureth unto everlaſting Life, which the Son of Man ſhall
give unto you.</hi> Which was to thoſe very Perſons that ſought after
him, to make him a King, and who had eaten of the Loaves and were fill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. For
though by thoſe hard ſayings, the Lord brake their deſign, yet from the
Word of the Lord it is plain, they were not to be forgotten by him: And whereas
the Lord ſaith, verſ. 39. <hi>This is the Father's Will which hath ſent
me, that of all which he hath given me, I ſhould loſe nothing.</hi> Again,
in the 40 verſ. <hi>And this is the Will of him that ſent me, that every
one which ſeeth the Son, and believeth on him, may have everlaſting
Life.</hi> That is every one that ſo believeth in the Son, as to walk in the
Precepts of the Son; it is likewiſe the Father's Will, that all ſuch may
have everlaſting Life, which is, if they continue in well doing; then will
the Lord raiſe them up at the laſt Day; which is the laſt, Day of the
Power of this wicked World. For God is not willing that Man ſhould periſh,
but that they ſhould come to Repentance, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9. But if we will
not deny our ſelves for Chriſt, Chriſt will deny us. And the Lord ſaith
in the 33d verſe, That <hi>he is the Bread of God that cometh down from
Heaven, and giveth Life unto the World:</hi> That is, to all that will take
hold<pb n="35" facs="tcp:93759:18"/>of the offered Mercy. And Chriſt ſaith, <hi>if he
be lifted up from the Earth, he will draw all Men unto him,</hi> John 12.32.
Which accordingly followed; for after the Lord's Aſcenſion, the Holy
Ghoſt was given to be in the Elect, whereby the World was convinced, that God
had ſent Chriſt, and ſo the Nations embraced the Faith, and by ſo
doing, became the Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and a great number, for the major
part in Scripture is reckoned as the whole; but afterwards, when the evil
Servants came to think the Lord delayed his coming, they began to ſmite their
fellow Servants, and to eat and drink with the drunken. <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.45.
But we building our Faith upon thoſe dark Sentences, which the Lord put
forth, thereby to leave <hi>Iſrael</hi> to Blindneſs, are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Blind our
ſelves alſo.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>XI. The Woman cloathed with the Sun: Or, The Woman in the
Wilderneſs.</head>
            <p>REV. 12.1. <hi>There appeared a great Wonder in Heaven, a Woman
cloathed with the Sun, and the Moon under her Feet, and upon her Head a Crown
of Twelve Stars.</hi> Now whereas it is ſaid, There appeared a great Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
in Heaven; a Woman. Firſt, I ſhall here ſhew you what, or who this Woman
is. This Woman is the Elect Church, or Remnant choſen from among
<hi>Iſrael,</hi> which had a peculiar Calling. 2dly, Why ſhe is ſaid to
be in Heaven. It is becauſe ſhe is highly favoured by the Heavenly Powers,
or Powers of Heaven, which is God. In being by him elected, fore-choſen,
ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſecured ſo by God, as none ſhall pluck them out of his
Hand, <hi>John</hi> 10.29. 3dly, Why ſhe is term<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Wonder. Was becauſe
there was none elected through the firſt or Old World, nor till the then time
that <hi>Iſrael</hi> was brought out of <hi>Egypt</hi> to be placed in the
heart of the Earth, and laid as a Foundation of the World to come. From which
Foundation, Chriſt<pb n="36" facs="tcp:93759:19"/>was figuratively ſlain in the
Paſchal Lamb: From which Foundation, the Works of thoſe unbelieving
<hi>Jews</hi> were finiſhed, when they through unbelief of the Promiſe of
God's giving them the Victory, refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to go to fight for the Land of
<hi>Canaan,</hi> for which, all that were numbred of them from twenty Years old
and upward, dyed in the Wilderneſs, ſave <hi>Caleb</hi> and
<hi>Joſhua.</hi> Now all <hi>Iſrael</hi> were taken into Covenant, and Life
and Death ſet before them, for them to chooſe Life, that they and their
Seed might live, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.19. But in the Wilderneſs they were
diſobedient, therefore they were cut off. After which God ſecured a Remnant
of that Foundation, which was then a laying in <hi>Iſrael</hi> for the World
to come: which is the World of which the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5.
And this exceeding kindneſs of God to this elect Remnant or Woman, was the
Wonder in Heaven: For this is the Foundation or Remnant choſen from the
Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which ſtandeth ſure, unto whom Chriſt promiſed to be with
to the end of the World; and that he would ſend them another Comforter, which
ſhould abide with them forever. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.16. This is more fully
proved and explained in the former Book. Therein is alſo ſhewed, that God
elected and choſe from among the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> a peculiar People, to the
praiſe of his Name, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.14 upon the firſt publication of the
Goſpel, who received the holy Ghoſt to be in them, that the World by the
evident witneſs of the Spirit might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that God ſent Chriſt, the
which was given for a ground of Faith, that thereby we might believe the Truth,
whereby a door of Mercy was ſet open to all Believers, that believe, like
<hi>Abraham,</hi> the promiſed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward is to be had in the way of their
Obedience; for Chriſt is become the author of Eternal Salvation to all them
that obey him, whether Elect or not Elect. Whereas it is ſaid in the 4th
verſe of this 12th chapter,<pb n="37" facs="tcp:93759:19"/>That the Elect Remnant, or
<hi>Woman was cloathed with the Sun:</hi> That is, ſhe was covered over with
the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of Chriſt, which was applicable before he was
Incarnate, or in the Fleſh, as well as afterwards; and in that ſhe is
ſaid <hi>to have the Moon under her Feet;</hi> thereby ſhewing the little
value ſhe has to all the changeable Vanities and Pleaſures of this World,
which is like the Moon; and therefore ſhe is ſaid to have the Moon under
her Feet. And in that ſhe is ſaid <hi>to have upon her Head a Crown of
twelve Stars,</hi> thereby ſignified the twelve Apoſtles, to whom was given
the prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minency, and in time to come the ruling power. And in that they are
termed the twelve Stars, is becauſe they were the firſt Publiſhers of the
Goſpel, by which many were turned to Righteouſneſs; and of ſuch it is
ſaid, <hi>They ſhall ſhine as the Stars for ever and ever,</hi> Dan.
12.3. <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.2. Now whereas it is ſaid, <hi>This Woman being
with-Child, cryed travailing in Birth, and pain to be delivered:</hi> That is,
of this Elect Remnant or Woman, as concerning the Fleſh, the Lord Chriſt
came. And in that ſhe cryed out, pained to be delivered, was her ardent
longing for Chriſt coming in the Fleſh, that by the Seed of the Woman, the
Serpents Head might be bruiſed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. But whereas it is ſaid
in the 3d. Verſe, <hi>There appeared ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Wonder in Heaven, a great Red
Dragon.</hi> When the Apoſtle ſaw this Viſion, this Dragon or Devil was
not then wholly caſt out from ſome part of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, as doth appear in
the 8th verſe. And whereas it is ſaid in verſ. the 4. <hi>That this
Dragon or Devil ſtood before the Woman to devour the Child as ſoon as it
was born.</hi> That was in that the Devil ſtir'd up <hi>Herod</hi> to ſeek
the young Childs Life, thinking to have deſtroyed him with the Innocent
Children. <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. <hi>And ſhe brought forth a Man Child which was
to rule all Nations.</hi> And therefore notwithſtanding all Satans attempts
this Child<pb n="38" facs="tcp:93759:20"/>was preſerved, till he himſelf freely laid
down his Life, by which he conquered Death, after which he was caught up unto
God and his Throne; according as it is ſaid <hi>Acts</hi> 1.9. <hi>He was
taken up, and a Cloud received him out of their ſight.</hi> And in
<hi>Heb.</hi> 8.1. It is ſaid, <hi>He is ſet at the right hand of the
Throne of the Majeſty in the Heavens.</hi> Rev. 12.6. <hi>And the Woman fled
into the Wilderneſs, where ſhe had a place prepared her of God, that they
ſhould feed her there a Thouſand Two Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and Threeſcore Days.</hi>
From whence we are to take notice, there is no mention made of the time, how
long it was before ſhe fled into the Wilderneſs after the Child was caught
up unto God.—Now having proved this forementioned Woman to be a Body of
People, as alſo the Scarlet Whore that ſits on many Waters is a Body of
People, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. And as the Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let Whore is termed a City, that
Reigns over the Kings of the Earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.18. So this Woman that is
clothed with the Sun, is likewiſe termed the Holy City, that ſhould be trod
under foot of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> Forty and Two Months, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.2.
Theſe <hi>Gentiles</hi> were the <hi>Gentiles</hi> that embraced the Faith,
which after they came to have no love to the Truth, but took pleaſure in
Unrighteouſneſs, and their Kings would not be holden with the Cords of the
Laws of the Lord, then God gave them up to ſtrong Deluſions, to believe
Lies, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.9,10,11,12. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.2,3. And then did the
Devil hoiſt up the Beaſt, by whom they were deluded and given up to
Worſhip him. (Whereas it is ſaid, <hi>The Holy City ſhould be trod under
foot of the</hi> Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles <hi>Forty and Two Months.</hi> From whence we are to
take notice that this Holy City is not of the <hi>Gentiles</hi>) And likewiſe
the Beaſt was to continue Forty and Two Months, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.5. And Forty
and Two Months, reckoning Thirty Days to a Month, according to the
<hi>Chaldean</hi> account, amounts exactly to a Thouſand Two 
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:93759:20"/>Hundred and Sixty Days, which is ſo many Days of Years;
The which time the Woman was to be fed in the Wilderneſs, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.6.
And a Thouſand Years is with the Lord as One Day, and One Day as a Thouſand
Years, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.8. And it is ſo Recorded to enlighten our
underſtanding in the Word. And alſo we are to take notice, that the
Promiſe of Chriſt was not that the Holy Ghoſt ſhould be in them for
ever, but with them for ever. So now this Remnant or Woman, which was drove
into the Wilderneſs, is as liable to fall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſome miſtakes, as the
Remnant choſen from among <hi>Iſrael</hi> was before Chriſt came; for
they did not appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend Chriſt coming to Suffer, neither do theſe his
coming to Reign; and likewiſe ſeveral great Truths in the Word, they did
not rightly underſtand the true meaning of them, ſo neither do theſe; but
the Promiſe of God was to them which were of the Remnant, that none ſhould
pluck them out of his Hand, which accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly God has performed, in
preſerving them in a holy and upright Converſation. And their Enemies
declare, that they were a People that walkt uprightly, and kept cloſe to all
the Commands of God. As for ſome in the Valleys that thro the Cruelty of
their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies were forc'd to adhere to the Beaſt, in the time of their
miſerable Deſtruction 1686. when they were expelled their Country, might be
ſome that did come to coinhabit with them, as often ſome of the <hi>French
Proteſtants</hi> did, for as St <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>If they had been
of them they would have continued with them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall hereafter by God's aſſiſtance, make appear who are
the two Witneſſes, or Olive-Trees, who continually gave the Oyl of Grace
out of themſelves into the Golden-Candleſtick, or Church, or Woman, who had
a place prepared of God in the Wilderneſs, that they ſhould feed her there,
<hi>Rev.</hi> 12.6. with Grace as aforeſaid. But as the Lord ſaid, <hi>The
Children o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:93759:21"/>this
World are in their Generation wiſer than the Children of Light,</hi> Luk.
16.8. For had this Woman and others of Chriſt's Servants that truly fear him,
underſtood the Word as well as the other did to get the Riches of this World
they had not taken up with ſuch miſtaken Notions as has been put upon the
Word.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <head>X. The <hi>Vaudois</hi> proved the Church in the
Wilderneſs.</head>
            <p>THe <hi>Vaudois,</hi> By the Hiſtory made of them, It is made
appear, that they never did adhere to the Beaſt. But have always lived in a
very ſtrict and Holy and upright Converſation, according to the Commands of
God, as the worſt of their Enemies, as it is recorded, has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared of them.
But by their often Wars, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſtations by Fire, occcaſioned by their
Enemies, they loſt the Scriptures, and Antient Records: So as the
An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cienteſt Acts that were preſerved from the Flames, was writ in 1100.
Called the <hi>Leſſon,</hi> As we may find in the late Hiſtory written
concerning them. In which <hi>Acts</hi> there is not ſo many miſtakes as in
their Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Faith made in the Year 1655. They ſince having
received other of the Miſtaken notions of their Proteſtant Neighbours. And
they not Apprehending the Foundations of the ſeveral Worlds, ſo think they
were choſen out of the Maſs or Lump of Mankind be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Foundation of
the Material world. But tho' they think they were then choſen, yet they do
not hold that God did then reprobate any. They alſo clear God from the
Miſcarriage of the Devil or Man. And declare God to be all Holineſs and
Goodneſs, and therefore he cannot be the Author of the Evil of Sin. And that
good works are ſo neceſſary to the faithful, that they cannot come to the
Kingdom of Heaven with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doing of them. pag. 19. <hi>Article</hi> 21. This
being accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to what the Apoſtles faith of them that were fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choſen 
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:93759:21"/>That God had fore ordained, <hi>That they ſhould walk in
good works.</hi> Ephe. 2.10. 1 Pet. 1.2. And this faith of Gods elect is
required in every true believer, ſo as they muſt believe the purchaſed
Redemption, and promiſed reward by Chriſt, is to be had in the way of their
obedience to him. For in believing that Chriſt is the Son of God, we are to
obey him as ſuch. For it is required of every true believer to do
whatſoever he Commands them. <hi>Matt.</hi> 28.20. For it is he that believes
in Chriſt and his word, that is the Diſciple, and believer indeed.
<hi>John.</hi> 8.31. But Chriſt did never require that all believers ſhould
believe that they were elected, or forechoſen. But thoſe that were elected
were by their good Works to be a light to the World, that others might follow
their good Example. For though they are now fallen into ſeveral and great
Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes concerning Chriſt's ſecond Coming, and ſeveral other things,
as well as the remnant of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore concerning
Chriſt's firſt coming. For the Lord did not promiſe that the Holy Ghoſt
ſhould be in them to the end of the World, but with them to the end of the
World, <hi>John.</hi> 14.16. Therefore they are now as liable to miſtakes, as
the remnant formerly were. But the Lord according to his promiſe, has kept
them from worſhiping the Beaſt, and has preſerved them in integrity and
Godly ſimplicity. So that none could pluck them out of his Hand. But through
the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interpretations put upon the Scriptures, they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived falſe
Notions. So according to the Word of the Lord in <hi>Eze.</hi> 34.18,19. The
Sheep of Chriſt have Eaten that which others have Troden, and Drank that
which others have fouled with their Feet. And that they have received other
Notions than what they had formerly, I ſhall here make appear. For in their
An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cienteſt Acts. 1100. Which is the Ancienteſt they now have, There it is
ſaid, That Chriſt dyed for all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers,<pb n="42" facs="tcp:93759:22"/>and ſo for
every one that believeth accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his word. And therein is nothing ſaid
of their being choſen before the Foundation of the World. And in thoſe Acts
it is ſaid, the Scriptures are the rule of Faith. And they being ſo, the
promiſed Reward is to be had by all that take hold of the offered Mercy,
ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Conditions as it is there tendred. And ſo not only the
Elect, but all believers, will be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the promiſed Mercy. But in
this latter Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith 1655. There they believe that Chriſt
dyed only for the Elect. And that Faith comes from the gracious efficacious
operation of the Holy Ghoſt, which Illuminates their Souls, and carries them
to relie on the Mercy of God to be applied by the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its of Jeſus Chriſt.
Yet they alſo in this Confeſſion hold that good works are ſo
neceſſary to the faithful that they cannot come to the Kingdom of God
without doing of them. And that they muſt keep the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments. But tho' in
this latter Confeſſion they believe that their Faith in Chriſt Jeſus
doth come through the efficacious work of the Spirit of God in them, the which
is not unlikely, becauſe more of the gracious Influence of the Spirit is with
them, by reaſon they were to withſtand all the fury of the Enemy, and to
continue to bear their Teſtimony againſt all the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious and
Idolatrous Worſhip of the Beaſt: And alſo to walk in a holy and exemplary
Converſation, that thereby they might be a Light to the World. As for Sins of
Ignorance, Sins of Infirmity, Sins of Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſal, will not be laid to their
charge, they being kept from wilful and preſumptuous Sins, which is the great
Tranſgreſſion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.13.</p>
            <p>And as in their Articles they ſay, This Church can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be quite
deſtroyed, but that it will always remain. This being according to what the
Lord hath promiſed them; they being the Church that the Lord prepared 
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:93759:22"/>a place in the Wilderneſs; and therefore they are of that
Remnant or Sheep, which were his Father's be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and given to him. To whom he
promiſed, <hi>That none ſhould pluck them out of his Hand,</hi> John
10.27,28. Thoſe are they to whom the Five Talents were given, that according
to their Day, they might have ability to ſtand. So that if any among them
have at any time fallen into a looſe or prophane Converſation, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hered
to the Beaſt; we may with St. <hi>John</hi> ſay, <hi>They were not of
them,</hi> (although they coinhabited with them in the Wilderneſs, in the
place the Lord prepared for them) <hi>becauſe they went out from them.</hi>
For had they been of that Fold to whom Chriſt made the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned
Promiſe, they would have continued with them, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.19. But
Chriſt ſaith, <hi>He hath Sheep of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Fold,</hi> that are not to be
brought into that Fold, until ſuch time there is but one Shephard, and then
<hi>there ſhall be but one Fold, and one Shepherd,</hi> Joh. 10.16. And that
will be when the Lord again comes. For tho' there was at the firſt
publication of the Goſpel a peculiar People<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> choſen from among the
<hi>Gentiles</hi> to the Praiſe of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Name; yet at that time there was many Shepherds<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But thoſe
peculiar People of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> had not
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> promiſe that none of them
ſhould be pluckt out of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hand;
and St. <hi>Paul</hi> cautions them, fearing leaſt the Ser<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pent ſhould
beguile any of them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.3.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Vaudois,</hi> as well as we, have loſt the righ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> apprehenſion of this World which is
to come, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> knowledge of which, was
as a Light that ſhineth in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dark
place, untill the Day dawn, and the Day-Star
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> riſe in their Hearts, which
is, an inherent perfect Righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teouſneſs will then be given, when the Lord
agai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> comes, the which crowns Life
to the Soul; not on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> to the
raiſed Saints, but to <hi>Iſrael, Iſa.</hi> 60.21. <hi>Thy Peop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall be all Righteous.</hi> And
alſo to the living Believer th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
longs for the Lords appearing, to all ſuch he will gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:93759:23"/>the Crown of Righteouſneſs at
that Day, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. The which things St <hi>Peter's</hi> care was,
they ſhould al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways have in remembrance after his Deceaſe, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi>
1.15. He fearing leaſt at any time they ſhould let them ſlip, which
ſince, for theſe many Years, is come to paſs, they having loſt the
knowledge of theſe things. But God having abounded in his Love to them, in
e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting and forechoſing them, without their foreſeen willing and running;
as he did likewiſe, at the firſt pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication of the Goſpel, chooſe a
peculiar People from among the <hi>Gentiles</hi> to the praiſe of his Name.
There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Vaudois,</hi> as well as us, by this their laſt
Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion have thought, that God had denied Man the freedom of Will to
will his own good; the which is quite contrary to what they held Two Hundred
Years before the ancienteſt Acts they now have were made, which were thoſe
in 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>00. for Two Hundred Years
before that time <hi>Claudius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Turin,</hi> and of the
<hi>Vallies,</hi> writ ſharply againſt all the Errors of the <hi>Church of
Rome.</hi> This Biſhop maintained the Doctrine of St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>
concerning Grace, as the late Author of the Hiſtory of the <hi>Vaudois</hi>
ſaith in Page 7. And <hi>Auguſtine</hi> tells us, <hi>lib. de. precat.
merit. chap.</hi> 18. <hi>That it was the great care of every Orthodox Teacher,
in his time, to take heed leaſt they did ſo defend Grace, as to deny
Freewill, and leaſt they ſhould ſo defend Freewill as to deny Grace.</hi>
(And a good care it was) and further the Author ſaith, <hi>Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there
(I think) to be found one of the ancient ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Orthodox that hath
maintained (in the ſtrict ſence oppoſed) that God commanded Men what they
could not do, with the common helps that he affordeth.</hi> But all abhorred it
as an Opinion, laying high accuſation upon God, till many Years after
<hi>Auguſtine,</hi> altho' <hi>Auguſtine</hi> did fall into miſtakes
himſelf as to this point, he not underſtanding how the Election ran. And
ſome of the Proteſtant Chriſtians not apprehending the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference 
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:93759:23"/>between the Eternal Life that Chriſt gave to his Sheep,
that were his Fathers before, and given to him, that unto them the Eternal Life
was given to continue to their Perſons and Poſterity: But the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life
that Chriſt gave to every true Believer, was no otherwiſe than whilſt
they did remain ſuch they ſhould never come into Condemnation; for a
Believer, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Goſpel, is no longer a Believer than he yields to
Chriſt his ſincere Obedience <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.16. St <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid to
them that had embraced the Faith, ſo as to yield O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience unto Chriſt,
<hi>Know ye not that Chriſt is in you, except you are Reprobates,</hi> 2 Cor
13.5. That is, except ye have rebelled by relinquiſhing your Obedience, and
ſo are become Reprobates, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> formerly had done; and
therefore ſaid of them, <hi>Reprobate Silver ſhall Men call them, becauſe
the Lord hath rejected them,</hi> Jer. 6.30. which rejection was for their Sin.
And the Prophet ſpeaking of the Body of the People that had wilfully
Tranſgreſſed, ſaith, <hi>All our Righteouſneſſes are as Filthy
Rags, and our Iniquities like the Wind have taken us away,</hi> Jſa. 64.6.
And the People of Gods Curſe to Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, will be them that will wilfully
perſiſt to do the thing which the Curſes in the Law were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonced
againſt, for although it is ſaid, <hi>All that are ſaved are ſaved by
Grace, and not of Works,</hi> that is to ſhow that we cannot perform good
Works to that perfection as to become juſtified by them, without the Merits
of Chriſt; and therefore ſaved by Grace, and not of Works; but Chriſt's
Righteouſneſs will be appli'd to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie his Creatures ſincere
indeavours, he being the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of Eternal Salvation to all thoſe that obey
him. But whereas it is ſaid, That it is not of Works of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs
that we have done, but according to his Mercy he ſaveth us, this was ſpoken
to the firſt Churches which was then brought out of darkneſs and hath no
reference to us, as is proved; but ſince the Nations have<pb n="46" facs="tcp:93759:24"/>fallen into Popery, we have not ſo underſtood as to
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh between that part of Scripture which hath a general tendency,
and that which hath not. And whereas Chriſt ſaid to the <hi>Jews, They
ſhould die in their Sins, except ye helievc that I am he,</hi> John 8.24. And
who is this he? but him that all the Prophets, and <hi>Moſes,</hi>
Propheſied of, <hi>That when that Prophet came they ſhould hear him in all
things whatſoever he commanded them,</hi> Acts 3.22. which at his firſt
coming they did not. And that all Believers that believe according to the Words
of Chriſt, ſo as to conſent to take his Yoke upon them, to become his
Servants, are then of his great Mercy and free Grace ſaved from their
original and paſt Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions by the Goſpel tender of his Grace,
<hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25. without their before performing the Deeds of the Law, for
Chriſt is become to ſuch Righteouſneſs, Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Redemption,
and by him the Eternal Life, loſt by <hi>Adam,</hi> reenters. But we are no
ſonner liſted his Souldiers and Servants, but we are to Fight, to keep our
Ground and Station wherein he hath ſet us; for the Eternal Life given to the
Believer, to make it an Eternal Inheritance, is a Prize ſet before us; and it
is the Runner that holds out to the end, and the War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rier that overcometh that
ſhall have the reward of the Crown of Life, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.11. <hi>And he
that puts his Hand to the Plough and looks back, is not fit for the Kingdom of
God,</hi> Luke 9.62. And it is ſaid, <hi>Remember</hi> Lots <hi>Wife.</hi>
And the Apoſtle ſaith of <hi>Himeneus</hi> and <hi>Alexander, That they
made Shipwrack of Faith and a good Conſcience,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.19. Likewiſe
others who were waſhed from their old Sins returned as a Dog to the Vomit;
and ſome denied the Lord that bought them, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.20,21,22. And
thoſe that live after the Fleſh, and deſpiſe Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, act as
irrationally as the Beaſts, for the Beaſts had not Reaſon given them, but
were made to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, <hi>ver.</hi> 12. And it is the Ground that
remains<pb n="47" facs="tcp:93759:24"/>barren, under the tender of Grace, and free offer of
Mercy, in the Call of the Goſpel, that is nigh unto Curſing, whoſe end is
to be Burned, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.6,8. And thoſe that receive the ſincere Milk
of the Word to grow thereby, are thereby brought off from the World and ſo
Regenerated and Born again, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2. But they which have not the
Word have not the Call of the Goſpel. And likewiſe among us who are not of
the Elect, there are ſome in a more peculiar manner brought home by the
operation of the Spirit of God upon them by the Word; but they do no longer
ſtand than they are found ſincere in their Obedience, <hi>Rom.</hi>
6.16.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <head>IX. The Word of the Scriptures is the Word of Faith, and in
them the offer of the Common Salvation.</head>
            <p>I Do alſo here affirm, that the Word of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures is the
Word of Faith, and in them the offer of the common Salvation; and whoſoever
believes the Truth of the Scriptures, they are able to make them wiſe unto
Salvation, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. Therefore the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith, <hi>It is
the power of God unto Salvation, unto every one that believeth; for therein is
the Righteouſneſs of God revealed, and the Juſt ſhall live by their
Faith,</hi> Rom. 1.16,17. <hi>For the Lord is become the Author of Eternal
Salvation to all them that obey him,</hi> Heb. 5.9. <hi>And by doing good Works
there is a laying hold of Eternal Life,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.19. as well as there was
ſome foreordained to Eternal Life. <hi>And the Word of the Lord endureth for
ever,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.25. <hi>The which we are to hold faſt till he come,</hi>
Rev. 2.24,25. And if the Word ſpoken by Angels was ſtedfaſt, and every
Tranſgreſſion and Diſobedience received a juſt recompence of Reward,
how ſhall we eſcape if we neglect ſo great Salvation? which at the
firſt began to be ſpoken by the Lord, and was confirmed to us by them that
heard him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.2,3. For the Lord Chriſt hath aboliſhed Death,
and hath brought<pb n="48" facs="tcp:93759:25"/>Life and Immortality to Light through the
Goſple, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.10. And the Apoſtle with <hi>Moſes,</hi>
ſpeaking of the Letter of the Word ſaith, <hi>The knowledge of it is in thy
Mouth, and in thy Heart, that thou mayeſt do it,</hi> Deut. 30.14. So that we
may do the thing that is there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, God having promiſed his
aſſiſtance, and that he will accept our ſincere Endeavour; and
whoſoever takes to the way therein directed will find the aſſiſtance
therein promiſed, with the aſſured Reward that Chriſt has purchaſed,
which they alſo will be partakers of, as well as thoſe that were
forechoſen, ſo as for any ones ſincere Service the Lord will be their
great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, when he again comes, at the time of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of the
purchaſed Poſſeſſion; for then will he Redeem <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and
give to others Rewards and Puniſhments according to their Deeds. And this is
the common Faith which all that are under the common Call of the Goſpel ought
to contend for, the which St. <hi>Jude</hi> terms the common Salvation,
<hi>verſ.</hi> 3. And it was by the common Faith that <hi>Titus</hi> became
ſo Eminent a Chriſtian, <hi>Titus</hi> 1.4.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <head>XII. How God is the Author of Faith in the Belief of the
Scriptures.</head>
            <p>BUT peradventure ſome will ſay, <hi>That we cannot of our
ſelves have Faith to believe the Scriptures, for that is the Gift of
Ged.</hi> Theſe Words were ſpoken to the Elect Church of the
<hi>Epheſians,</hi> who were part of the peculiar People choſen from among
the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> for the Praiſe of his Name, which received the Holy
Ghoſt to be in them, who were then firſt brought out from the Abominations
of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and to whom the Apoſtile ſaith <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.8.
<hi>For by Grace ye are ſaved thro' Faith, and that not of your ſelves, it
is the gift of God.</hi> That is, it was the great Mercy and rich Grace of God,
the<pb n="49" facs="tcp:93759:25"/>gift of his Son; and this great Mercy is to be received
thro' Faith, which Faith is not of themſelves, it is the gift of God, who
unto them in a peculiar manner he did at firſt manifeſt himſelf to; but
God did never leave himſelf without vvitneſs for the ground of Faith, to
confirm the truth of vvhat he vvould have us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve; and therefore to confirm
the Lavv, that it vvas his VVill and his VVord, he Gloriouſly and Terribly
appeared on Mount <hi>Sinai;</hi> and to confirm the Goſpel, he firſt
ſent dovvn the Holy Ghoſt in cloven Tongues like Fire, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.2.
And then becauſe that vvould not be a ſufficient Evidence to the VVorld
vvhat vvas done at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> altho there vvere then ſome of all
Nations there then preſent, yet notwithſtanding for the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
confirmation to the World, that God had ſent Chriſt, he therefore took from
among the <hi>Gentiles</hi> a People for his Name at the firſt viſiting the
<hi>Gentiles</hi> by the Goſpel, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.14. Who through the
conviction of the Spirit upon the word of the Diſciples, <hi>believed in
Chriſt through their Word, John</hi> 17.20. And the Word in this place,
Chriſt terms their Word, becauſe they received it from the Mouth of the
Diſciples, and believed it; God having then given them no other outward
viſible Teſtimony than what they had from the Diſciples, whoſe Word
they believed, and ſo were Baptized. And afterwards the Holy Ghoſt was
given to be in them, according to the Promiſe of the Lord, <hi>John</hi>
14.17. by which they were glorified, ver. 22. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2. And became
united to God by partaking of that one Spirit that the World might believe that
God had ſent Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 17.21,22,23. by the mighty Power, Signs
and Wonders that were ſeen among them. Theſe were thoſe that were
foreknown, called, juſtified, and glorified, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29,30 by their
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the Holy Ghoſt to be in them, by which their Bodies became the
Temples of the Holy Ghoſt. Theſe<pb n="50" facs="tcp:93759:26"/>were thoſe, that when
they were brought before Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours and Kings, were to take no thought how or
what they ſhould ſpeak, for it ſhould be given them in that Hour what
they ſhould ſpeak, for the Spirit of the Father ſpake in them,
<hi>Mat.</hi> 10.19,20. For the Holy Ghoſt which, was but with the
Diſciples, was afterwards given to be in the Diſciples and firſt
Churches, <hi>John</hi> 14.17. chap. 17.21. So then the World did not believe
in Chriſt through the alone word of the Diſciples, but through the evident
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of the Spirit of God, which was evidently and viſibly
manneſt in the Elect by their Speaking with Tongues, and working of Miracles;
ſo as the World thereby might have ſufficient Evidence to believe that God
had ſent Chriſt: And thus was the Prayer of Chriſt fulfilled, in <hi>that
the World might believe that God bad ſent him, John</hi> 17.21. And the
Goſpel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus wonderfully eſtabliſh'd, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.4. Therefore
we ought to give the more earneſt heed to the things is they were firſt
delivered, and not as we firſt received them. And the care of the Lord was
ſuch, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he commanded his Diſciples to teach all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. yet notwithſtanding they were for bidden by the Spirit
to preach the Word in <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Bythinia, Acts</hi> 16.6,7. till
ſuch time the Elect were called in, that by their receiving the Holy Ghoſt
to be in them, they might be a Light to the World. And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards the Word was
preached in <hi>Aſia,</hi> and believed on there, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. And St.
<hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, That <hi>the Goſpel had been preached to every
Creature under Heauen,</hi> Gol. 1.10,23. And <hi>that their ſound went
through the World,</hi> Rom. 10.18. And that the World embraced the Faith in
the Apoſtles time, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.16. And their ſtanding was, as they
continued in the Faith, and were not moved away from the hope of the Goſpel,
by which the promiſed Hope is attained. And upon the perfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of this
condition<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> God will never forſake any<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for<pb n="51" facs="tcp:93759:26"/>as
the Lord is the Author of Faith, ſo to them that obey him, he will be the
Finiſher, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2. chap. 5.9. (the word <hi>our</hi> in this
Verſe, is not in the Greek.) And whereas St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, That
<hi>none can ſay that Jeſus is the Lord, but by the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> 1
Cor. 12.3. This the Apoſtle ſpake when the Goſpel was firſt
publiſh'd, at which time the Holy Ghoſt was given for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of
the truth thereof. But ſince, the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> have learned to
ſay by rote, that Chriſt is the Son of God, without the aſſiſtance of
the Holy Ghoſt. And whereas the Apoſtle ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14.
<hi>The natural Man receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God, for they are
fooliſhneſs to him, neither can be know them, becauſe they are
ſpiritually diſcerned.</hi> That is, whilſt the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Man gives
himſelf to ſenſual delights, as the pleaſures and profits, and other
advantages of this life, which in the 6th <hi>verſ.</hi> is termed <hi>the
wiſdom of this world,</hi> he will not give himſelf a liberty to conſider
his ways to be wiſe. And therefore ſuch cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the knowledge of
the things of God, becauſe they are ſpiritually to be diſcerned, that is
by a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering Spirit, or a Spirit of Conſideration: And therefore God
often calls to Man to conſider their ways, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.29. <hi>Job</hi>
34.27. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.22. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.3. Chap. 5.12. <hi>Ezek.</hi>
18.14,28. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 7.2. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.5. And
alſo St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. <hi>If any Man among
you ſeemeth to be wiſe, let him become a Fool that he may be Wiſe: For
the wiſdom of this world is fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with God.</hi> But by our
forſaking the Vanities, Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and ſubtil Craftineſs of the World,
is the way to become wiſe in Spiritual things. And if ye <hi>reſiſt the
Devil, he will flee from you, draw nigh to God, and he will draw nigh to you
James</hi> 4.7,8. And <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> by making the Law of God his Meditation,
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came wiſer than all his Teachers, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.99. And <hi>if any
man lack wiſdom, let him ask of God, who giveth<pb n="52" facs="tcp:93759:27"/>and
upbraideth not, and it ſhall be given him,</hi> James 1.5. <hi>If thou
crieſt after knowledge, and lifteſt up thy Voice for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding: If
thou ſeekeſt her as Silver, and ſearcheſt for her as for hidden
Treaſures, then ſhalt thou underſtand the Fear of the Lord,</hi> Prov.
2.3,4,5. <hi>Wiſdom is the principal thing, therefore get wiſdom, and with
thy getting, get <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding. She ſhall give to thine Head an Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of Grace, a Crown of Glory ſhall ſhe deliver to thee,</hi> chap. 4.7,9. But
the worldly wiſe men, the Apoſtle ſaith, will be taken in their own
Craftineſs, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.19. And whereas the Apoſtle ſaith, verſ.
7. <hi>Neither is he that planteth any thing, neither is he that watereth, but
God that giveth the encreaſe.</hi> This he ſpake upon the firſt
publication of the Goſpel, upon the calling in of the Elect, which great
increaſe God gave by a fore-appointment, of whom he ſaid, <hi>they knew
God,</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are known of God, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.9. Becauſe they were
thoſe that were fore-choſen. For herein he had his reference to the then
time, which was the great Day of Salvation, when the Elect were called in, and
a Door of Mercy ſet open to the World, that they might take hold of the
offered mercy in the common Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; The which the Nations did, and ſo
became the Seed of <hi>Abraham.</hi> But they that were made the Temple of God,
<hi>if any of them defiled the Temple of God, him would God deſtroy,</hi> 1
<hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16,17. For St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles had their peculiar
tendency to them of that time, to whom he wrote, who then had turned from
worſhipping dumb Idols to ferve the living God, who was then in a more
peculiar manner brought home, and was then juſtified through the Imputation
of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs in the Belief of the Truth, without their
before performing the Deeds of the Law, ſo as none might charge them for
their Sins that were paſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25. but then they were to walk in
newneſs of Life. Theſe were thoſe that were ſaved, <pb n="53" facs="tcp:93759:27"/>not for Works of Righteouſneſs which they had done, <hi>Tit.</hi>
3.5. Thus was a Door of Mercy ſet open, not only to the Elect that had the
peculiar Calling, but alſo to the World that had the general Call by the
Goſpel, and believed like <hi>Abraham</hi> the Word of the Lord. And as he
for ſook his Country, his Kindred, and his Father's Houſe: So were the
Chriſtians to forſake all the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of this preſent evil world; the
which accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly they did. And the Lord knew that <hi>Abraham</hi> would
command his Children and his Houſhold after him, that they ſhould keep the
Ways of the Lord, to do Juſtice and Judgment, that the Lord may bring upon
<hi>Abraham</hi> that which he had ſpoken of him, which Promiſes were to be
performed upon Conditions, the which conditions he fulfilled. So likewiſe the
firſt Churches generally obeyed, and commanded their Children and Houſhold
after them to keep the ways of the Lord, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.1,2,3. and to walk
blameleſs; and they were to hold faſt that which they had received, till
the Lord comes, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.25. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.17,18,19,20. But when the
<hi>Chriſtians,</hi> as <hi>Iſrael</hi> formerly had done, forſook his
ways, they then became eſtranged from God, and ſo their Children became
<hi>eſtranged from the Womb, and ſtopping their Ear like the deaf Adder,
who will not hear the Voice of the Charmers, charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing never ſo wiſely,
Pſal.</hi> 58.4. Here we ſee their Ears were no otherwiſe ſtopt, than
as they ſtopt them them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: And ſuch as harden themſelves in Sin,
and will not do juſtly, God chooſes to harden them in blindneſs, and
unbelief of the truth, and ſuch will be the Veſſels of his Wrath and
ſore Diſpleaſure. But as for thoſe that have not ſo hardned
themſelves in Iniquity, ſo as to become thereby under a ſtupid ſence,
let them ſeek to God for his aſſiſting Grace, that thereby they may be
enabled to withſtand Sin, that they may not be guilty of the like again; and
then will not the Prayers<pb n="54" facs="tcp:93759:28"/>of the Wicked be ſin, when they
go to God to ask Forgiveneſs for that which they never intend to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
again; but it is their Prayers are abomination and Sin, who ask Forgiveneſs
for thoſe Sins which they intend to commit again.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <head>XIII. Concerning being Born again.</head>
            <p>WHereas Chriſt ſaid to <hi>Nicodemus, John</hi> 3.3. <hi>I
ſay unto thee, except a Man be born again, he cannot ſee the Kingdom of
God.</hi> Here Chriſt doth not ſay every Man muſt be born again that
ſeeth the Kingdom of God; but ſuch a Man, or Men, as <hi>Nicodemus,</hi>
that had em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced this preſent World, and valued the praiſe of Men, and
ſo aſhamed to own Chriſt, and therefore came to him by Night; ſuch
muſt be born again, or brought off from the World, or they cannot enter into
the Kingdom of God. But whereas the Lord ſaith, verſ. 5. <hi>Except a Man
be born of Water and the Spirit, he cannot enter into the Kingdom of God.</hi>
In this Verſe he doth not ſay that all that enter into the Kingdom of God
muſt be born again, altho all that enters, muſt be born of the Spirit: For
ſome were born after the Spirit from their Mother's Womb, as <hi>John
Baptiſt, Luke</hi> 1.41,44. and <hi>Jeremiah, Jer.</hi> 1.5. And the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet
<hi>David</hi> ſays, <hi>God made him hope when he was upon his Mothers
Breaſt,</hi> Pſal. 22.9. And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from his
Mother's Womb, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.15. <hi>Acts</hi> 26.5. And all the Children of
Believers are ſaid to be Holy, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. that is before they
commit actual Sin. Likewiſe Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Suffer the little Children
to come unto me, for of ſuch is the Kingdom of God,</hi> Mark 10.14. Mat.
18.10,3,4. Therefore no need of their being born again: But as the Lord had a
Figurative mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his ſaying, <hi>a man muſt be born after the
Spirit;</hi> So it was here but a Figurative Speech, in that he ſaid, <hi>a
Man muſt be born again;</hi> for the Lord had here no <pb n="55" facs="tcp:93759:28"/>reference to the natural Birth; for firſt, thoſe that are
Religiouſly brought up, and walk all along in Integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and do not wilfully
corrupt their way, ſuch are born after the Spirit, and thoſe that like the
Prodigal, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from home, thereby they become born after the Fleſh; ſuch
muſt be regenerated, that is to ſay, born again, or they cannot enter into
the Kingdom of God. And tho' there is original defilement in all Children; ſo
the beſt of Saints are not here without Sin, but Chriſt will take away
Original Sin from both, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.20. And whereas Chriſt ſaith,
<hi>John</hi> 3.8. <hi>The Wind bloweth where it liſteth.</hi> The Lord had
here his more peculiar refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the time when the Elect were to be brought
home by the inward touch of the Spirit upon the heart, which then in a more
wonderful manner the Spirit like the Wind blew where it liſteth. Now
<hi>Nicodemus</hi> being one of the Rulers of the <hi>Jews,</hi> unto whom
Chriſt always ſpake in dark Sentences and Parables; <hi>And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a
Parable he ſpake not unto them,</hi> Mat. 13.34. And all that Chriſt here
ſaid to him, was ſo Myſtical that it appeared to him as a Paradox. But no
doubt after the Lord's Aſcenſion, but thoſe Rulers that deſired the
knowledge of the Lord before he ſuffered, believed on him when the Goſpel
was taught, and the Scriptures opened. But before theſe Myſtical Sayings of
Chriſt were opened, they ſeemed to contradict what before they had
received, and therefore they could not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve. And it is ſaid,
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 53.2,3. <hi>God looked down from Heaven upon the Children of
Men, to ſee if there were any that did underſtand, that did ſeek God.
Every one of them is gone back, they are altogether become filthy, there is
none that doth good, no not one.</hi> From theſe words, it is plain that they
might have ſought God, and God did expect better from them, but they were
gone backward, and became filthy through their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault. But with theſe
that were gone back, the Elect Remnant were not reckoned<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For at that time
God<pb n="56" facs="tcp:93759:29"/>ſaid of them that were gone back, <hi>that they did
eat up his People as they eat Bread,</hi> verſ. 4. And God's People in
Scripture are termed the Sons of God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not reckoned with the
Children of Men. And tho' God has concluded all under Sin, ſo as none can be
ſaved without the Imputation of Chriſt's Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Rom.</hi>
3. But whereas St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith in the 10th and 11th Verſe; Wherein
he could have no reference to the Remnant. For he ſaith, <hi>There was none
Righteous, no not one.</hi> There was none that ſought after God. For if he
did here include the Remnant, he did not herein ſpeak agreeable to what is
written; for God in the <hi>Pſalm</hi> ſaith the contrary. Therefore St.
<hi>Paul</hi>'s meaning here, was of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Nation, and not of
the Elect Rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. But after the Lord came, there doth appear by Scripture, to
be a larger number of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in this Election of Grace then was
before; which was ſinful, and had corrupted their way, as well as the
<hi>Gentiles,</hi> but to all that feared God in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> was the
Word of this Salvation ſent, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.26. From whence it is clear,
there was then ſome of them in <hi>Iſrael</hi> that then alſo feared God.
And Chriſt by the Parable of the Ninety Nine Sheep, from whence is made
appear they were ſafe by the Promiſe of God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15. <hi>Who
ſhall abide in thy Tabernacle,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And to all that order their
Converſati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> aright, he will
ſhew his Salvotion,</hi> Pſal 50.23. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt ſaith,
<hi>He came not to call the Righteous, but Sinners to Repentance,</hi> Luke
5.32. For they were not then to be called home, for ſuch were his Father's
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. As for that one Sheep that went aſtray, we are to take notice, that
the nature of Sheep is not wilfully from their Companions to wander away; but
the Prodigal that wilfully left his Father's Houſe, firſt look<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> home, before his Father lookt on him,
<hi>Luke</hi> 15.18. Now what St. <hi>Paul</hi> goes to prove from the
Prophets, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20,21,22,23. was to prove their Juſtificatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from their paſt Sins, through the
Blood of Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:93759:29"/>verſ. 24.25. Without their before performing the deeds of
the law; for had not God then juſtified them by the alone Imputation of
Chriſt's Righteouſneſs in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of the Truth, they could not then
have been ſaved; for then not only the Gentile World lay in Wickedneſs, but
the elect alſo that was choſen from among them lay in Wickedneſs.
Therefore God at the then time, to declare his Righteouſneſs, verſe 26.
which was in his being juſt to his Promiſe made to <hi>Abraham,</hi> in
bringing in the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile Nations to be Heirs with <hi>Iſrael.</hi> And
therefore at the then time, at their firſt calling in they were juſtified
from their paſt Sins by believing in Jeſus accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the word, and
Faith in his Blood, verſe 22.25. That they and their Children might be
brought in Heirs with <hi>Iſrael</hi> according to the Promiſe,
<hi>Gen.</hi> 17.4. And as <hi>Abraham</hi> after God had called him, was
commanded to walk before him in a perfect and upright way, verſe 1. which
accordingly he did, and ſo became Heir to the Promiſes, verſe 2.7. And
ſo the Lord ordered his Diſciples to go and teach and baptize all Nations,
that they ſhould teach them to obſerve all things whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he
commanded them, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19,20. And whilſt they ſo did they were
Heirs to the Promiſes. And theſe things, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, were
witneſſed by the Law and the Prophers, verſe 21. For <hi>Moſes</hi>
wrote concerning it. And in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 55. The tender of the common
Salvation was Propheſied of that all that were a thirſt might come, buy and
eat without Money, and without Price, that is, tho there was nothing then in
them to render them acceptable, but a thirſting after the Lord with a
wearineſs of their Sins, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.28. And if they did <hi>hearken
diligently unto the Lord, and eat that which is good, and let their ſoul
delight it ſelf in fatneſs, and incline their ear and come unto him and
bear, and their ſouls ſhall live,</hi> verſe 23 Here we are to take
notice that they were to thirſt when they heard of<pb n="70" facs="tcp:93759:30"/>the
offered Mercy, and then they were to incline their ear, and come unto him, and
when they were come they were to hear, that is, all that he by his word
commanded them, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.20. And if they did hear, and eat that which
is good, then upon the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of theſe Conditions, the Lord will make
an everlaſting Covenant with them the ſure Mercies of <hi>David,</hi> The
which will be when the Lord again comes, at which time God will eſtabliſh
his promiſed everlaſting Covenant with <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed,
together in their Generations, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. And God alſo by the
Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet declares the pouring forth of his Spirit, not only at the ſecond
coming, but alſo at the firſt coming of Chriſt, <hi>Joel</hi> 2.28,29.
And St. <hi>Paul</hi> concerning the then fore-mentioned time, <hi>Rom.</hi>
3.26. mentions <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 49.8. applying theſe words of
<hi>Iſaiah</hi> to the then time, as in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2. <hi>I have heard
thee in a time accepted, and in the day of ſalvation have I ſuccoured
thee.</hi> Behold now is the accepted time, behold now is the day of Salvation.
But afterwards when the <hi>Gentiles</hi> came to have no love to the Truth,
for which they were given up to Deluſion, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.10. Then it
was not the great day of Salvation, which falling away was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo fore
propheſied of <hi>Pſalm</hi> 2.2,3. And in divers other places; for thoſe
that God calls will not be accepted when the times of refreſhing ſhall come
from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord, without their now improving in this time
their day of Grace under the call of the Goſpel; for when the Lord comes, we
that have the knowledge of him muſt appear before the judgment Seat of
Chriſt, that every one may receive the things done in his body according to
that he hath done, whether it be good or bad, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. <hi>For
God-without reſpect of perſons judgeth according to every mans work, paſs
the time of your ſojourning here in fear,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.17. And the
promiſed reward was to them that held out to the end, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.10. 
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:93759:30"/>That they ſhould receive a Crown of Life; that is, be
ſaved with an everlaſting Salvation, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> will be when the
Lord again comes, who then <hi>ſhall not be aſhamed, world without end,
Iſaiah</hi> 45 17. And this is the world to come, of which all the Apoſtles
ſpeak of, and which is to be put in ſubjection unto Chriſt in time to
come, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5. But as St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, God before ſhewed
by the mouth of all his Prophets that Chriſt ſhould ſuffer, he hath ſo
fulfilled, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.18. <hi>Whom the heavens muſt receive until the
times of the reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of all things.</hi> Which he likewiſe ſaith,
God hath ſpoken by the mouth of all his Holy Prophets ſince the world
began, verſe 21. Which beginning of the world was <hi>Iſrael,</hi> unto
whom <hi>Moſes</hi> declared it, verſe 22. And they will be the world
without end, when the Lord hath eſtabliſhed his new everlaſting Covenant
with them that they ſhall not ſin againſt him, and then they will never
more fall under Condemnation; therefore ſaid to be world without end. And
unto this Promiſe the <hi>Gentile</hi> Chriſtians conditionally were
brought in Heirs with <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="chapter">
            <head>XIV. Part of the Chriſtians Miſtakes.</head>
            <p>NOW ſince the Roman Apoſtacy, the Chriſtians have built
their Faith on thoſe Parables that Chriſt ſpake to put out the Eyes of
<hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Underſtanding; and alſo on thoſe miſtaken places of
Scripture that our Predeceſſors ſince Popery have loſt the true meaning
of, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Chriſtians fancying that all that was ſaid
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Remnant and firſt Churches, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> at the
reſtitution of all things, that they now belong to them, and are made good to
them in this time, although they find not in them what is there promiſed; but
many vainly imagine through their miſtaken Notions, that they are now ſo
ſecured by Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, as they cannot finally fall away,
and ſo little regarding the plain words of Chriſt, as his Sermon on the
Mount, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. to the eighth Chapter. And alſo that he laid 
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:93759:31"/>down his life for the world, <hi>John</hi> 3.17. And his
gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Invitation to accept of Salvation, by taking his Yoke upon them,
<hi>Matth.</hi> 11.28,29. And Chriſt faith, If thou wilt enter into Life,
keep the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.17. And in loving God and our
Neighbours, hangs all the Law and the Prophets, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.4. And is
commanded us by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.13. And not the
hearers of the Law are juſt before God, but the doers of the Law ſhall be
juſtified; and it is ſaid, to the Law and to the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, if they
ſpeak not according to this word, it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is no Light in them,
<hi>Iſaiah</hi> 8.20. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore St. <hi>Peter</hi> terms it, <hi>a more
ſure word of propheſie where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto ye do well, that ye take heed, as unto a
light that ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in a dark place, until the day dawn, and the day ſtar
ariſe in their hearts,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.19. For in the Prophecies is declared
the promiſes of the bleſſedneſs in time to come, in which time will be
given an inherent perfect righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which is the day Star that will
then ariſe in their hearts, for in time to come is given the eternal life, 1
<hi>Tim.</hi> 6.19. Now the <hi>Bereans</hi> were ſaid to be noble, becauſe
they ſearched the Scriptures, to ſee if thoſe things which were ſpoken
by the Apoſtles were ſo or no, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.11. And the Scriptures then
was only the Old Teſtament, and all the Propheſies were to be fulfilled,
and as many of them as has not yet been fulfilled, remains ſtill to be made
good, in as much as it is impoſſible for God to lie, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.18.
<hi>Jer.</hi> 31.33,34,35,36,37. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.9,10,11. Chap. 62.8. much
leſs forſworn, and Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Think not that I am come to
deſtroy the law and the prophets, I am not come to deſtroy but to fulfil;
for verily I ſay unto you, till heaven and earth paſs, one jot or one
tittle ſhall in no wiſe paſs from the law, till all be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled,</hi>
Matth. 5.7,18. That is, not till all the great Promiſes and Propheſies that
are written in the Law and the Prophets are fulfilled, both as to the
Puniſhments<pb n="73" facs="tcp:93759:31"/>and the Glory that ſhould follow,
<hi>Dan.</hi> 7.27. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 60.21. Which promiſed Glory could never
come to paſs, had not the Lord laid down his Life to purchaſe to himſelf
a glorious Church in time to come, without ſpot or wrinkle; but that it
ſhould be holy and without blemiſh, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.27. <hi>Iſaiah</hi>
60.21. And according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> it is declared, and in the
<hi>Rev.</hi> 5.10. For the glorious time will not be till <hi>Iſrael</hi>
receives the Promiſes. Now all our miſtaken Notions are quite contrary to
the Law and the Prophets and therefore not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by us; and though
Chriſt Aboliſhed the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial Law, it was no ways contradictory to the
Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets; for <hi>David</hi> Typically ſpeaking of Chriſt, ſaith,
Sacrifice an Offering thou deſireſt not, then ſaid I, lo I come in the
volume of the Book it is written of me, <hi>I delight to do thy will O
God.</hi> Pſalm 40.6,7. Chriſt was that acceptable Sacrifice which only
could take away Sin, which the Sacrifices of the Ceremonial Law could not do,
and therefore were to be Aboliſhed, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20.25. But whereas
Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.13. All the Prophets and the Law
Propheſied until <hi>John,</hi> which was becauſe the Ceremonial Law was
then to be Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, and then part of the Propheſies was fulfilled in
Chriſt's firſt coming; but there is other of the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies are ſtill
to be fulfilled, which not only foretels the Lord's ſecond coming, but alſo
what will be in time to come, agreeable to which the Lord Revealed to St.
<hi>John</hi> by Revelation. Now though the <hi>Gentiles</hi> were not
commanded the outward Circumciſion, yet there is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of them the inward
Circumciſion of the Heart, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.29. The performance of which has
been lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle obſerved; but unto this Circumciſion, Baptiſm is a Figure,
and though we keep the eighth day, or otherwiſe call'd the firſt day for
our Sabbath, yet this is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to the Scripture; for when God
bleſſed the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath Day, he pronounced the Bleſſing to the Sabbath 
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:93759:32"/>Day, not naming the ſeventh Day in the Bleſſing; but
in that God ſaid the Seventh Day is the Sabbath of the Lord thy God; from
hence it doth not appear that it ſhould remain ſo for ever and ever. Which
words are added to that which is ſo to continue, and the eighth Day was the
great Day of the Feaſt, which was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Sabbath,
which was a Figure of the great Feaſt or Sabbath in time to come, unto which
their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Circumciſed on the eighth Day doth allude, in which God will
Circumciſe their Hearts that they ſhall no more Sin againſt him by the
then Eſtabliſhing the promiſed new everlaſting Covenant which Crowns
Life to the Soul, which Covenant now is but a Covenant of Promiſe, but when
Eſtabliſhed, God's People will be all Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and then it is
<hi>Iſrael</hi> will inherit the Land for ever, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 60.21. And
this God declaring we are bound to believe, in as much as it is imppſſible
for God to lie, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.18. And God never left himſelf without
Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to confirm the Truth of his Word, that we might have Ground for
Faith; for by that time moſt of the Elect among the <hi>Gentiles</hi> were
taken off by Death, <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was deſtroyed, and the <hi>Jews</hi>
became a ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red People through the World, according as God by the
Prophets, and Chriſt hath declared, and which is to this day evidently known,
and that they were thus ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered becauſe of their Sins; this the whole
Book of God declares, and themſelves acknowledge, and by them the Scriptures
of the Old Teſtament have been more ſafely preſerved all along amongſt
the Nations, whilſt the Nations were deprived of the New Teſtament by the
Pope, and ſo loſt the right apprehenſion of the meaning of the things
therein contained, and likewiſe the Ordinances ſpoken of, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi>
11.2. Which he praiſes them for keeping them as he delivered them; the which
St. <hi>Peter</hi> foreſeeing according as by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet is declared, that
the Goats would eat the good<pb n="75" facs="tcp:93759:32"/>Paſtures, and tread the
reſidue with their Feet, and foul the deep Waters, <hi>Eze.</hi> 34.17,18.
Therefore St. <hi>Peter</hi> terms the Writings of the Prophets a more ſure
Word of Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, whereunto ye do well to take heed, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19.
And the Scriptures declare concerning <hi>Iſrael,</hi> firſt their Riſe,
their Continuance, their ſcattering, and there remaining ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered till
the Meſſiah again comes, and there being ſuch a ſcattered People among
us, and through the whole World who acknowledge the Law and Prophets in the
truth of theſe things, it is certainly evident to us and the whole World that
the Scriptures are true, and the Word of God; and to confirm the Truth of what
God hath there declared, he hath given us a Sign in the Heavens, Signs upon the
Earth, and under the Earth, and thro' the World. But for Brevity ſake I
ſhall here mention but three, which are evidently known to all. Firſt, That
the old World for Sin was drowned, the Rainbow in the Heavens doth witneſs to
the Truth of the Word. Secondly, God declareth that his Anger ſhould ſet on
fire the Foundations of the Mountains, which ſhould burn to the loweſt
Hell, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.22. Which for theſe many hundred years is come to
paſs, and alſo that Hell ſhould enlarge her ſelf, <hi>Iſaiah</hi>
5.14. Which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe few years is wonderfully come to paſs by the
Rivers of Fire, Pitch and Bitumen which has been ſent out thence, the which
doth likewiſe bear witneſs to the Truth of God's Word, and alſo
<hi>Iſrael</hi>'s being ſcattered doth witneſs to the World the Truth of
the ſame.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="chapter">
            <head>XV. Chriſt proved to be the Son of God.</head>
            <p>BUT peradventure ſome will ſay, how can we prove the New
Teſtament to be true, and Chriſt to be the Son of God, ſeeing the
<hi>Jews</hi> do not own it. I ſhall not here go to prove it from the Words
of the Apoſtles, as to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it through their bare Word; but I chiefly
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it, becauſe I find thoſe things that were fore Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſſed of
by the Prophets concerning the Meſſiah,<pb n="76" facs="tcp:93759:33"/>made good in the
Crucified Jeſus, unto which ſure word of Propheſies we are always to take
heed. And in that the Scriptures now again being rightly underſtood, they are
not contradictory to what God before ſpake by the Prophets; for we are to
believe nothing in contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to what God hath ſpoken by the Prophets,
for what God hath abſolutely promiſed, he will certainly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form. And
therefore to declare his Righteouſneſs in the performance of his Promiſe,
he ſent the Son of his Love to Suffer for Sinners, as was declared by the
Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and that for <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s wilful Diſobedience, he was then
a Stone of Stumbling, and a Rock of Offence to both the Houſes of
<hi>Iſrael,</hi> for a Gin and for a Snare to the Inhabitants of
<hi>Jeruſalem, Iſaiah</hi> 8.14. Which accordingly ſo fell out; for they
expecting he ſhould come as a King, and not apprehending that he ſhould
firſt come to Suffer, therefore he was Deſpiſed and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected of Men. A
Man of Sorrows, and acquainted with Grief; they hid as it were there Faces from
him, he was deſpiſed, and they eſteemed him not, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 53.3.
And it was Propheſied concerning him, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 7.4,15,16. That a
Virgin ſhould conceive and bear a Son, and that he ſhould be born in
<hi>Bethlehem,</hi> Mic. 5.2. And lowly Riding upon an Aſs. <hi>Zach.</hi>
9.9. And the Lords Sufferings and Death were likewiſe foretold;
<hi>Iſaiah</hi> 53 7 <hi>He was brought like a lamb to the ſlaughter, and
as a ſheep dumb before the ſhearers; ſo opened he not his mouth,</hi>
Zach. 11.12,13. <hi>And they weighed for his price thirty pieces of ſilver,
Pſ.</hi> 22 16,18. <hi>And they pierced his hands and his feet,</hi> Dan.
9.26. <hi>And the Meſſiah was cut off, but not for himſelf;</hi> all
theſe hings, and many more were made good in the Crucified Jeſus. Therefore
I believe him to be the Meſſiah, that Seed of the Woman that ſhould
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>iſe the Serpents Head,
<hi>Gen</hi> 3. <hi>And that Lord unto whom the Lord ſaid, ſit thou on my
right hand till I make thine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Pſ. 110.1. Which will be when the Lord again comes to
deliver his People. And for<pb n="77" facs="tcp:93759:33"/>further Proof that this Lord is
God, God ſaith, <hi>Zech.</hi> 13.7. <hi>Awake O ſword againſt my
ſhepherd, and againſt the man that is my fellow, ſaith the Lord of
hoſts.</hi> And none can be the fellow of God, but the Son of God, which is
God, and therefore ſaid of him that Was to be born in <hi>Bethlehem, that his
goings forth have been from of old from everlaſting, Mic.</hi> 5.2. And of
him it is ſaid, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto us a child is born, and unto us a ſon is given,
and the government ſhall be upon his ſhoulders, and he ſhall be called
the wonderful counceller, the mighty God, the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Father, the prince
of peace,</hi> Iſaiah 9.6. And when this Prince of Peace ſhall come and
take the Government, then will he be to all his Sheep the everlaſting Father,
<hi>and the God of the whole earth ſhall he be called,</hi> Iſaiah 54.5.
And of this Prince of Peace it is ſaid, <hi>Thy throne O God is for ever and
ever, the ſcepter of thy kingdom is a right ſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, thou loveſt
righteouſneſs, and hateſt wickedneſs; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God thy God hath
anointed thee with the oyl of gladneſs above thy fellows,</hi> Pſalm
45.6,7. And according to this the Apoſtles declare of Chriſt the Lord, that
he is God; for they were not, nor did not hold any thing in contradiction to
what God hath declared by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and what is declared of God in the Old
Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, there is nothing contrary thereunto in the New. And as the Holy
Spirit was ſpoken of throughout the Old Teſtament, ſo likewiſe in the
New only ſometimes called Holy Spirit, ſometimes Holy Ghoſt, which is all
one; it being the Breath of God, which is called the River of God, the Streams
whereof ſhall make glad the City of God, the Holy Tabernacle of the moſt
High, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 46.4. Which pure River of Water is ſaid to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
out of the Throne of God and of the Lamb, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.1. therefore this
River giveth Life and maketh glad. Now as there is Figurative Heavens and Earth
ſpoken of in the Old Teſtament, ſo there is alſo in the New; and as
there is a Figurative Sea made mention of in the Old Teſtament, ſo
likewiſe in the New; for there is in both<pb n="78" facs="tcp:93759:34"/>ſeveral
Figurative Expreſſions which have one and the ſame meaning, aluding to
one and the ſame thing in both, which I have fully made appear in my Book of
the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurative Speeches, therefore I ſhall not inſiſt here up on it. But
God did not only ſpeak myſtically to <hi>Iſrael</hi> concerning
Chriſt's firſt coming, becauſe for their Sins they might be ſnared,
broken and taken; but the ſecond coming of Chriſt is alſo to us now,
ſince we have loſt the true meaning of the word, theſe things appear very
myſtical in the New Teſtament to us, that the wicked of the Adopted Seed,
whoſe turn it is now to be ſnared, broken and taken for God by the Law, and
Goſpel ſpeaks to them that under it (as I have fully made ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear from the
Scriptures in my Book of the Explanation of the New Teſtament) and they are
the World that will be Judged by it, and the Wicked of them that will not live
in, Obedience to it, are the World that will be then Condemned by it. The which
the Chriſtians not apprehending, they put the Day of Judgment far off,
expecting the Fall of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the Reſtoration of
<hi>Iſrael</hi> to be before the Lord comes, the which will not be till after
the Lord comes; as I have fully made appear in the fore-mentioned Book. For
<hi>Idumea</hi> will be the Figurative Heavens with their Hoſts that will be
deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 34.4,8. When <hi>Iſrael</hi> is Reſtored;
which <hi>Idumea</hi> in the Revelation is termed myſtical <hi>Babylon,</hi>
and the Figurative Heavens and Elements which will be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed,
<hi>Rev.</hi> 6.3,4. And the Heaven and Earth that will paſs away, with which
are included the reſt of the Wicked that know his Laws; for the Covetous Man
is ſaid to be an Idolater, as well as he that Worſhips an Idol,
<hi>Eph.</hi> 5.5. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.5.</p>
            <p>And thoſe that walk after the Luſt of the Fleſh will fall
under the Condemnation; for the Wicked ſhall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, and the Enemies of
the Lord ſhall be as the Fat of Lambs, they ſhall conſume, into ſmoke
ſhall they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume away, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 37.20. And we reckon our
Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies<pb n="79" facs="tcp:93759:34"/>always to be them that knows us, and not them that
knows us not. And St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Charge was that they ſhould be mindful
of the words that were ſpoken before by the Holy Prophets, and of the
Commandment of us the Apoſtles, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.20. Which was, that they
might not be ignorant of the coming of the Lord, which the Scoffers are
willfully ignorant that by the word of God the Heavens were of old, and the
Earth ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the Water and in the Water; whereby the World that
then was being overflowed with Water then periſhed, verſe 5.6. The which
World was the World of People, and then they were not diſtinguiſhed by
Heavens and Earth, for then there was no Ruling Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers but what belonged to
Parents over their Children and Families; and therefore alike termed the World,
and not the Heavens and Earth As <hi>Iſrael</hi> was not termed Heavens and
Earth, till they became a Ruling Power and People. So likewiſe the Heathen
when they became a Ruling Power and People, then were they termed a Heavens and
Earth, as I have already proved, but in that St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, the
Heavens and Earth that are now by the ſame word are kept in ſtore,
reſerved unto Fire againſt the Day of Judgment, and perdition of ungodly
Men, verſe 7. But in that he ſaith, the ſame Heavens and Earth which are
now are kept in ſtore un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Judgment. Therefore he had no reference here to
thoſe that were of old; and the Figurative Heavens which was then in the
Apoſtles time, was the Roman Power, by which the Servants of Chriſt were
then op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt, and it is the Roman Power which are now like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe their
Afflictors, and will remain till the Lord comes, and then will they be
deſtroyed with Fire, with the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the reſt of the ungodly Men,
who knowing the Laws of the Lord will not obey them. And then not only the
fore-mentioned Heavens and Earth of People will be burnt up; that is, that
pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t of the Earth where the 
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:93759:35"/>devouring Storm cometh, mentioned, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 11.6.
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the wicked he ſhall rain ſnares, fire and brimſtone, and an
horrible tsmpeſt; and then it is the hail will ſweep away the refuge of
lies,</hi> Iſaiah 28.17. Whereby it ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth there will be Hail mixed with
Fire, as was in <hi>Egypt, Exod.</hi> 9.23,25. For the Storm of Hail in
<hi>Iſaiah,</hi> and the Storm of Fire in the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> hath
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts tendency to one and the ſame
time. And this Hail is ſaid to come down on the Forreſt, <hi>Iſaiah</hi>
32.19. At which time <hi>Iſrael</hi> and the reſt of the Nations that are
ſaved will be ſafe in <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Land whilſt the Earth is
renewing, as I have largly proved in the fore-mentioned Book of the Figurative
Speeches. But becauſe the Adopted Seed to whom this is ſpoken, have 
<q rend="inline">'tranſgreſſed the Laws changed the
Ordinances, therefore the Curſe devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the Earth, and the Inhabitants
thereof burned, and few Men left,' <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 24.5,6.</q> That is, few
Men will be found Righteous among the fore-mentioned, ſo as to be left when
the other are deſtroyed; for this Earth of People that has ſo wilfully
offended <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Tranſgreſſions 
<q rend="inline">'thereof ſhall be heavy upon it, and it ſhall
fall and not riſe again,' verſe 20.</q> So as in the firſt Judgment there
will be ſome Sentenced to everlaſting Puniſhment, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as the Lord
by the Parable declares, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.46. And the wilful Oppoſers of
the Truth will like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be raiſed to receive their Condemnation; for then
the Saints will riſe to everlaſting Life, and ſome to Shame and
everlaſting Contempt, <hi>Daniel</hi> 12.2. For they that neglect the greater
Salvation, fall under the greater Condemnation. For then the Heathen Powers of
Rome, or otherwiſe called Heavens that wilfully reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Truth, when
the Holy Ghoſt was given for the Confirmation thereof, will riſe to receive
Puniſhment, and therefore likewiſe ſaid to be kept in ſtore, as well as
the Heavens of the Chriſtian Rome, which has made Lies their Refuge. For
theſe ſdumean Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens,<pb n="81" facs="tcp:93759:35"/>or myſtical <hi>Babylon</hi>
will be the Heavens that will be on Fire, and the Elements that will melt with
fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent heat, of which St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpake. But he ſaith,
<hi>neverthel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſs we according to
his promiſe look for new hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens and a new eaerth, wherein dwelleth
Righteouſneſs,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.12,13. For the Apoſtles always had
their Eye to the Propheſies, as not to teach in contradiction to the
Promiſes. And God ſaith, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 65.17,18. <hi>For behold I
create new heavens and new earth, and the former ſhall not be remembred, nor
come into mind. But be you glad and rejoyce for ever in that which I
cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate;</hi> for behold I create <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> a rejoycing, and her
People a joy. And becauſe God would have us take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice what this is that he
here Creates; he therefore ſaith, Behold I Create <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> a
rejoycing, and her People a joy. This is the new Heavens and new Earth that God
Created upon the old Foundation, the which is <hi>Iſrael,</hi> of which
Foundation Chriſt is the chief corner Stone. And why is it here ſaid that
God will Create new Heavens and new Earth; becauſe they are ſuch Heavens
and ſuch Earth as was never here ſuch before, as to have Righteouſneſs
dwelling in them, as will be when <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> is made a rejoycing,
and her People a joy. For when Chriſt firſt came, the ruling Power was not
gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him, though he had then Righteouſneſs dwelling in him and it is
ſaid theſe Heavens came down from above, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 45.8. <hi>Drop
down ye heavens from above, and let the skies pour down righteouſneſs, let
the earth open, and let them bring forth ſalvation, and let righteouſneſs
ſpring up together, I the Lord have created it.</hi> This Righteouſneſs
the Lord Creates when he comes down with all his Saints, which are the Heavens
that comes from above; then will he pour down Righteouſneſs, and then the
Earth of his People will bring forth Salvation, and then Salvation and
Righteouſneſs will ſpring up together.<pb n="82" facs="tcp:93759:36"/>For the
Covenant is to them and their Children, and to as many of us as are found in
our Obedience, and in that day God will appoint Salvation for Walls and
Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warks, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 26.1. Thus the Prophets and Apoſtles agree that
Salvation will be when the times of Refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhall come from the
preſence of the Lord, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19,21,22. And Chriſt ſaith,
<hi>Search the ſcriptures, for they were they that d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d teſtifie of him,</hi> John 5.39. And then there was
no other Scriptures but the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Now all Chriſt's Sufferings
being fulfilled in the plain Letter of the Word, and left us upon Record ever
to believe the ſame. And as in the Word it is Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied that
<hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhould be ſcattered, ſo we evidently ſee the ſame;
and we ought alſo, and are bound to believe all the great Propheſies and
Promiſes relating to Chriſt's ſecond coming, that they will be performed
in the plain Letter of the Word, and as it was Propheſied that God would pour
forth his Spirit, <hi>Joel</hi> 2.28,29. Of which St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith,
<hi>It was made good to them in that time,</hi> Acts 2.16,17,18 Which was for
the Confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Goſpel, and as an earneſt of their Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in
time to come, or Reſtitution.</p>
            <p>Before which time, as in <hi>Joel</hi> 2.30,31. <hi>God will
ſhew wonders in heaven and in earth, blood and fire, and pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of ſmoke,
which accordingly has come to paſs, for by wars much blood hath been ſpilt.
And the Lord in a great and wonderful manner hath ſent out of the earth fire
and pillars of ſmoke for theſe many hundred years, but much more of
late.</hi> And it is ſaid, <hi>verſe</hi> 31. <hi>The ſun ſhall be
turned into darkneſs, and the moon into blood, before the great and terrible
day of the Lord come.</hi> This came to paſs when the Nations which had
embraced the Faith came to have no love to the Truth, God then gave them up to
Deluſion, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.10,11. <hi>For when the people could not
endure ſound doctrin, but after their own luſts they did<pb n="83" facs="tcp:93759:36"/>heap to themſelves teachers, having itching ears, and they turned
away their ears from the truth, and were turned un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to fables,</hi> 2 Tim. 4
3,4. <hi>And when the Seducers and falſe teachers went about to deceive, they
then became de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, ch.</hi> 3.12,13. For God doth never ſo puniſh
without a cauſe, <hi>Eze.</hi> 14.23. And then was the Sun turned into
darkneſs; for in the Scriptures the Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are termed the Light of the
World, and when the Sun the Teachers were darkned, the Moon which is the World
of People which receiveth her Light from the Teachers, as the Moon doth her
Light from the Sun, the People were ſoon turned into Blood, by ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and
killing one another. The Pope and his Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy pretending to be the true Church,
<hi>Mahomet</hi> the true Prophet, and every Sect the right Remnant; and thus
the Prince of Darkneſs carries on his Deſigns, in ſetting Men to hate and
kill one another through theſe Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. (Now in that Propheſie of
Scripture is of more than a private Interpretation, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20. But
we muſt be ſure to put no other Interpretation on it, but what we can make
plain from the Word. And in <hi>Joel</hi> 3.15. It is alſo ſaid, <hi>The
ſun and moon ſhall be darkned, and the ſtars ſhall withdraw their
ſhining.</hi> Here the Prophet may have a Reference to the material Sun, Moon
and Stars, which by the Glorious Appearing of the Lord will be obſcured by
his Brightneſs.</p>
            <p>But when the Nations came to have no love to the Truth, God
ſuffered a Spirit of a ſtrong Deluſion to go forth, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi>
2.11. <hi>For God hath determined, that thoſe that will not deny themſelves
for him ſhall ſuffer by him; for unto them that are contentions, and will
not obey the truth, but obey unrighteouſneſs, indignation, and wrath upon
every ſoul of man that doth evil, of the Jew first, and alſo of the
Gentile; but glory honour and peace to every man that work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth good, to the Jew
firſt, and alſo to the Gentile,</hi> Rom. 2.8,9,10.<pb n="84" facs="tcp:93759:37"/> For
there will be a Redemption in time to come, for all that order their
Converſation aright, and have not been wilful Oppoſers of the Truth, which
is one of the worſt of Unrighteouſneſſes. And though it is thoſe who
comes in Heirs to the Promiſes made to the Fathers that are made partakers of
the greater Glory, yet there is Glory and Salvation for others of a lower
degree. And though the <hi>Jews</hi> that have been ſince Chriſt's time
were caſt off for the Sins of their Parents, yet not for ever and ever to be
forgotten of God, without their own Sins does occaſion it; for there will be
a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption in time to come for ſome; and if <hi>Iſrael</hi> for the Sin
of their Parents has been left to ſtumble on the dark Mountains theſe
ſeventeen hundred years, no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if the Adopted Seed has been left to
ſtumble thereon for above this thouſand years. For it is <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
who as touching the Election, is beloved for their Fathers ſake,
<hi>Rom.</hi> 11.28. For though there was but a Remnant choſen from among
them that were choſen according to the Election of Grace, verſe 5. Yet they
were all Gods choſen and elected People for their Fathers ſake,
<hi>Iſaiah</hi> 45.4. And this God did becauſe he loved their Fathers,
becauſe they had walked with a perfect Heart before him. The which, when the
Lord proved <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Wilderneſs they did not. And therefore
the Lord ſaith, <hi>Deut.</hi> 31.21. <hi>For I know their imaginations which
they go about, even now before I have brought them into the land.</hi> Here
becauſe God would have us take notice when it was he knew it; therefore he
redoubles his Words, and ſaith, even now at the time when they were in the
Wilderneſs. But we do never read of God's foreknowing his Drowning of the
World, till he ſaw the Wickedneſs of Man was great, and then it was that it
grieved him at his Heart that he had made Man; but God's chooſing
<hi>Iſrael</hi> was for their Fathers ſake, and not that he had Elected
them without a why or a where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore;<pb n="85" facs="tcp:93759:37"/>but when God had proved
and tryed <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Wilderneſs, and as they had there often
miſcarried; God ſaw they would again fall away, for which he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to
leave them to Blindneſs; the like God fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing that the
<hi>Gentiles</hi> would fall away, for which he determined to leave them to
Deluſion. For as of old when the People fell away, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.18,20,21.
<hi>the wrath of God is revealed from heaven againſt all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſs and
unrighteouſneſs of men, who hold the truth in unrighteouſneſs. For the
inviſible things of him from the creation of the world are clearly ſeen,
being underſtood by the things that are made even his eternal power and
godhead; ſo that they were without excuſe, becauſe when they knew God,
they glorified him not as God, but became vain in their imaginations, and their
fooliſh heart was darkned, verſe</hi> 28. <hi>And even as they did not like
to retain God in their knowledge, God gave them up to a reprobate mind.</hi> So
we ſee Man's not improving his Day of Grace, has been his Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all
along; and not that they had not a Day of Grace given them; and it is ſuch
that God gives up to Deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that firſt deceives and deludes
themſelves, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.7. <hi>And like not to retain God in their
knowledge, but in the way of well doing, we may commit the keeping of our
ſouls unto God, as unto a faithful creator,</hi> 1 Pet. 4.19. Now St.
<hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking of the Creation of the World, in the fore-going Words,
<hi>Rom.</hi> 1.20. makes menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it as ſuch, and not as the Foundation
of the World. And all the Apoſtles in all their Writings, agree in cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
the Twelve Tribes the Foundation of the World to come. And likewiſe
<hi>Zachariah</hi> the Prieſt ſaid, God hath raiſed up a Horn of
Salvation in the Houſe of his Servant <hi>David.</hi> Here he doth not ſay
that this was Propheſied of from the Foundation of the World, but by all the
Holy Prophets ſince the World began, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.69,70. <hi>That he would
raiſe up a horn of ſalvation in the houſe of his ſervant David.</hi>
And in <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:93759:38"/>was the Typical
Kingdom of Chriſt. And after <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> had received the Kingdom, God by
the Prophet, ſaid, <hi>His ſeed ſhall endure for ever, and his throne as
the ſun before me,</hi> Pſalm 89.36. This <hi>ever,</hi> is the ever of the
time to come, the which all the Prophets Propheſied of from <hi>David</hi>
till Chriſt came; but no Prophet Propheſied that this Salvation ſhould
come out of the Houſe of <hi>David,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>David</hi> was, and had
received the Kingdom. But we not apprehending the difference between the
Creation and Foundation, nor the beginning of this World to come, has caſt us
into moſt dangerous Miſtakes; for thereby we have received another Faith,
than what the Goſpel teacheth, in thinking none but the Elect can be ſaved,
and that ſome thereby have thought they ſhould be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the
Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, contrary to the Words of Chriſt, which are
upon the condition of their O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, which will prove deſtructive, if
unrepented of. Likewiſe we have another Hope than what the Scripture
Teacheth; for by our Predeceſſors falling in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Popery, we have loſt the
form of ſound words, as they were firſt delivered; and to maintain our
receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed miſtaken Notions we muſt not believe what God hath declared,
promiſed and ſworn to. And this out of pretence of juſtifying God's
Wiſdom, which ſome ſay doth greatly conſiſt in God's ſore-knowing
all the Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs of the Devil and Man from all Eternity; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they
make God the firſt conceiver of it; and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe with ſuch approbation,
as ſome ſay, as he did not only ſuffer it, but decreed it to be
committed; which is ſo quite contrary to the Holy God, as the thoughts
thereof are to be abhorred, it being Blaſphemy for to think it, for he hath
abſolutely declared againſt it. For it was after God ſaw that Man had
corrupted his Way, it repented him that he had made Man upon the Earth, and God
ſaid <hi>it griewed him at his heart, Gen.</hi> 6.6. Now whether it is right
in the ſight of God, to believe Man<pb n="87" facs="tcp:93759:38"/>rather than God, judge
ye, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.19. And that God that is an unchangeable Being, in
Holineſs, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Juſtice, Goodneſs and Truth, which are his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
Attributes, and therefore impoſſible for God to lie, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.18.
<hi>For God is not a man that he ſhould lie, neither the Son of Man that he
ſhould Repent;</hi> that is, when God hath abſolutely promiſed, a
Bleſſing, he will certainly perform it, as it is here declared. <hi>Hath he
ſpoken, and ſhall he not make it good? Numbers</hi> 23.19. And we are to
believe of God in every thing, as he hath declared of himſelf; to be moved to
pity upon Man's Repenting and Returning, and to Anger and Wrath upon Man's
Rebellion; and of certain, God will never be angry with any for believing what
he ſaith, or hath promiſed or ſworn to. And the Prophet for believing
what another Prophet told him, in contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction to what God had declared to
him, a Lyon met him and Slew him, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 13.17,18,24. And as the
Faith of <hi>Abraham</hi> was ſet down for our Example, ſo this was
Recorded for our warning, that we might not believe Man in contradiction to
God. Now Chriſt and the Apoſtles being rightly underſtood, are found to
agree with the Words of God and the Prophets; and the Care of the Apoſtles
was ſuch, as to <hi>compare ſpiritual things with ſpiritual things,</hi>
1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.13. To ſee if the Spirit ſpake in them agreeably to what
the Spirit ſpake in the Prophets of old, that thereby no Deluſion or
Deceiver might creep in among them; for God did never ſend his Son, and the
Servants of his Son, to contradict what he himſelf hath declared, promiſed
and ſworn to.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="chapter">
            <head>XVI. The Glory and Bleſſedneſs that will be in time to
come.</head>
            <p>For the Lord will come to judge the Nations in the val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley of
<hi>Jehoſaphat,</hi> and reſtore his People <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Joel
3.1,2,12,13,16,17,18 and then it is the Lord will make Mount<pb n="88" facs="tcp:93759:39"/>
               <hi>Sion and eternal excellency, and the joy of many
Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations,</hi> Iſaiah 60.15. And then it is <hi>his people ſhall be all
righteous, and inherit the land for ever.</hi> Then it is a <hi>little one
ſhall become a thouſand, and a ſmall one a ſtrong nation, the Lord will
haſten it in his time, Iſaiah</hi> 60.21,22. Here the Lord ſheweth there
will be another time after this time, in which his People will be bleſſed;
againſt which time St. <hi>Paul</hi> ordereth <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,</hi> that he
ſhould <hi>charge them that are rich in this world, that they be rich in good
works, laying up for themſelves a good foundation againſt the time to
come,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.17,18. And ſure if we were not blind, we could
not think that all that are Rich in this World are Elected; but that by doing
good Works, all may lay hold of eternal Life, 
<q rend="inline">'for Chriſt is become the Author of eternal
Salvation to all them that obey him,' <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.9.</q> Whether Elect or
not Elect, but thoſe that remain blind, now God has made plain his Word, is
becauſe they have no deſire to ſee; but whether ſome will ſee or not,
it is in the time to come that God will make that promiſed new e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting
Covenant with his People, <hi>and put his laws in their inward parts, and write
them in their hearts, and they ſhall teach no more every man his neighbour,
and every man his brother, ſaying, know ye the Lord; for they ſhall all
know me from the leaſt of them to the greateſt of them, ſaith the
Lord,</hi> Jer 31.33,34. <hi>And in that day the Lord will make a covenant for
them with the beaſt of the field, and with the fowls of heaven, and with the
creeping things of the ground,</hi> and then will the Lord <hi>break the bow,
the ſword, and the battel out of the earth.</hi> And then will the Lord
betroth <hi>Iſrael to him for ever in righteouſneſs, in judgment, in
loving kindneſs and in mercy,</hi> Hoſ. 2.18,19. And then the days of his
People ſhall be the age of a Tree, and then it is the Meek ſhall inherit
the Earth, and delight themſelves in the abundance of Peace, and then it is
the evil Beaſts will ceaſe out of the Land, <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 34.25. 
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:93759:39"/>Now this Covenant, ſome have blindly imagined that it is
made with them, although they do not find any of thoſe things here promiſed
made good to them. Such like <hi>Ephraim</hi> feed on Wind, but the Lord will
eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh this promiſed Covenant when he Reigns in Mount <hi>Zion,</hi>
and in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and before his Ancients Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly,
<hi>Iſaiah</hi> 24.23. Which will be when <hi>he gathers his wheat into his
garner, and burns up the chaff with unquench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able fire;</hi> which is at the
time when he will <hi>judge the nations in the valley of Jehoſaphat,</hi> and
at the time when the Saints are raiſed, which are called <hi>the firſt
reſurrection,</hi> Rev. 20. And then will the new <hi>Jeruſalem come down
out of heaven from God,</hi> and be placed in the elementary Heavens, 2
<hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1. <hi>This is the tabernacle which the Lord pitched, and not
man,</hi> Heb. 8.2. <hi>The pavement of which is of pure gold, as it were
tranſparent glaſs,</hi> through which the glorious Saints <hi>will then
ſhine forth as the ſun in the kingdom of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> Matth. 13.43.
And when this 
<q rend="inline">'World is become the Kingdom of our God and of his
Chriſt,' <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15.</q> 'Then will it become the Kingdom of their
Father, and 
<q rend="inline">'then, in the ages to come, God will ſhew forth
in them the exceeding Riches of his Grace,' <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.7.</q> That they 
<q rend="inline">'ſhould be to the praiſe of his Glory that
firſt truſted in Chriſt,' <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.12.</q> And likewiſe all that
overcome and 
<q rend="inline">'keep his Works to the end, ſhall ſit with
Chriſt in his Throne,' <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.21.</q> For the Glorious Tabernacle
will be Chriſt's Throne, as the Heaven of Heavens is God's Throne, and this
Glorious Tabernacle, is the Tabernacle or Covert ſpoken of in
<hi>Iſaiah,</hi> which the Lord will place over all the Aſſemblies of
<hi>Iſrael,</hi> when he cleanſeth their Blood, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 4.4,5,6.
which he hath not yet cleanſed, <hi>Joel</hi> 3.21. And the Glory of the
Saints in this glorious Tabernacle, the Apoſtle had a Refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to, when he
ſaid, 
<q rend="inline">'God hath provided ſome better thing for us,
that they without us ſhould not be made perfect,' <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.40.</q>
And the glorious Saints Perfection<pb n="90" facs="tcp:93759:40"/>will not be till
<hi>Iſrael</hi> receives the Promiſes; for when the Lord comes again, the
dead Bodies of the Saints will be Raiſed, and then under Chriſt their Head,
will be given to them their ruling Power upon Earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.10. For
then they will with Chriſt Deſcend from the glorious Tabernacle, as the
Lord formerly did in the Cloudy Pillar to the Tabernacle in the Wilderneſs;
ſo likewiſe will the Lord Deſcend upon the real Mount <hi>Zion,</hi>
which the Lord <hi>will make an eternal excellency, and the joy of many
generations,</hi> Iſaiah 60.15. <hi>And then will the Lord deſtroy in this
mountain the face of the covering caſt over all people, and the vail that is
ſpread over all nations;</hi> for then <hi>he will take away the ſting of
death from all his people, which is ſin, and the rebuke of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
ſhall he take away from off all the earth,</hi> Iſaiah 25.7,8. But when
Chriſt firſt came, he was laid <hi>in Zion as a ſtumbling ſtone,</hi>
and thereby a Vail was caſt upon the Face of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and they were
made the Rebuke of all the Heathen. But when the Lord again co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>es, <hi>he will then take away the
covering off of all faces, and the rebuke of his people from off all the
earth;</hi> and then <hi>his people Iſrael will be all righteous, and inherit
the land for ever,</hi> Iſaiah 60.20,21. <hi>For the Lord hath ſaid, he
will gather them out of all countries, and will plant them in this land
aſſuredly, with my whole heart, and with my whole ſoul,</hi> Jer.
32.37,38,39,40,41. And at the time of the Judgment of this World it is, that
unto the Son of God will be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>dominion and a kingdom, that all people,
nations and languages ſhould ſerve him; his dominion is an everlaſting
do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion which ſhall not paſs away, and his kingdom that which ſhall not
be deſtroyed,</hi> Dan. 7.14 And then ſhall be the end of the Wicked of
this World, <hi>when the ſon of man ſhall ſend his angels, and they
ſhall gather out of his kingdom all things that offend, and them that do
iniquity,</hi> Matth. 13.40,41. Therefore it is clear, according to the Word of
the Lord,<pb n="91" facs="tcp:93759:40"/>in <hi>Daniel</hi> 7.27. That this Kingdom which
ſhall be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, is under the whole Heaven, from whence 
<q rend="inline">'thoſe that Offend, and them that do Iniquity
will be gathered out, and caſt into a Furnace of Fire after the Lord
comes,'</q> and the Angel flies <hi>in the midſt of heaven, having the
e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting goſpel to preach unto them that dwell on the earth, ſaying
with a loud voice, fear God, and give glory to him, for the hour of his
judgment is come, and worſhip him that made heaven and earth, and the ſea,
and the fountains of waters,</hi> Rev. 14.6,7. And then will <hi>Iſrael</hi>
and the Heathen Nations that know not God be called in, which will be after the
Lord comes, and juſt before <hi>Babylon</hi>'s Fall, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.1,8.
And this was the Kingdom that St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Endeavour was, that the
Elect Remnant to whom he Wrote, <hi>might be able after his deceaſe to have
theſe things always in remembrance,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.11,12,13,15. This is the
World to come, of which St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5. And
this is the Kingdom the Angel told the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Virgin of, <hi>that Christ
ſhould reign over the houſe of Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob for ever, and of his kingdom there
ſhall be no end,</hi> Luke 1.33. But this Kingdom will not be, until the
times of Refreſhing ſhall come from the Preſence of the Lord, and then
'tis that the <hi>kingdom and dominion, and the great neſs of the kingdom
under the whole heaven ſhall be given to the people of the ſaints of the
moſt high, whoſe kingdom is an everlaſting kingdom, and all dominions
ſhall ſerve and obey him,</hi> Dan. 7.27. When the Lord taketh to
him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf his own great Power, and Reigneth; the which will be when the
ſeventh Angel ſoundeth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15,16,17. And then it is that the
Raiſed Saints will like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Reign under Chriſt their Head, Chap. 5.10.
And then to <hi>Iſrael</hi> and the People under them will be given the
Kingdom, they being the People of the Saints of the moſt High.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:93759:41"/>
               <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.10. And that ye may approve
things that are excellent, that ye may be Sincere, and without Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence till
the day of Chriſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="chapter">
            <head>XVII. Who they were that were made able Miniſters of the New
Teſtament, not of the Letter, but of the Spirit.</head>
            <p>AND whereas the Apoſtle ſaith, 
<q rend="inline">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5,6. 'Not that we are
ſufficient of our ſelves, to think any thing as of our ſelves, but our
ſufficiency is of God;'</q> that is, without God we can do nothing, 
<q rend="inline">'for in him we live, move and have our being,'
<hi>Acts</hi> 17.28.</q> And if he take away our breath, we dye; but as God
hath made us Rational Souls, and given us his Law, ſo as to underſtand
thereby his Will in his Word, and God by ſo doing has made us capable to do
ſomething; but in that he ſaith, verſe 6. <hi>God hath made them able
miniſters of the new Teſtament, not of the letter, but of the ſpirit; for
the letter killeth, but the ſpirit giveth life.</hi> Now the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles
received their Knowledge immediately from the Lord Chriſt, and alſo of the
Spirit, for the Holy Ghoſt was given to be in them, by which they alſo
under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood things to come; and by the Spirit they were made able
Miniſters, not of the Letter, but of the Spirit; for all the
<hi>Gentiles</hi> when they were firſt to be called in, had he then Preach'd
the Letter of the Law to them, they then had thereby all been Condemned. But
the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles were upon the firſt Publication of the Goſpel, to Preach
Remiſſion of Sins by Chriſt, to every one that would turn from their evil
way, and by that turn they were to live in obedience to the Letter of the Word.
And in that he ſaith they were made able Miniſters of the New Teſtament;
was in that the Holy Ghoſt was then given as a Witneſs to their
Teſtimony, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the Truth of their Word, and likewiſe they did
Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter the Spirit; for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
the laying on the Hands of the Apoſtles, the People received the Holy
Ghoſt,<pb n="93" facs="tcp:93759:41"/>
               <hi>Acts</hi> 19.6. <hi>And when Paul had laid his
hands upon them, the holy Ghoſt came on them, and they ſpake with tongues
and propheſied.</hi> So alſo, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.17. But ſhould any Man now
pretend to Preach ſuch Doctrin of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtring the Spirit, and not the
Letter of the Word, the People had good reaſon to believe that Man was out of
his Senſes. But ſome have given ſuch a turn to theſe Words of the
Apoſtle, from hence pretending they are not to take the plain Letter of the
Word as it is ſpoken, but according to the Spiritual Interpretation which
they have put upon it; the which has been according to their own Fancy. And
ſo by leaving the plain Letter of the Word in what God hath declared,
promiſed, and ſworn to, are thereby fallen into theſe great and dangerous
Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes; for the Scripture admits of no other Spiritual Meaning, than what
is there ſpecified; which is, that we perform not the Letter or practical
part of the Word to be ſeen of Men, but in ſincerity of Heart, ſo as to
Worſhip God in Spirit and Truth. But in the Word there are many Figurative
Speeches, which admits of no other Interpretation than what can be made out
from the Word, leaving nothing therein to contradict what we ſay. And
likewiſe ſome have got another way to uphold their falſe received
Notions, which is, that God ſpeaks after the manner of Men, and according to
Man's Underſtanding; and if ſo, how doth any Man dare to open another
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ay for Man to underſtand of God,
than what God thought fit for Man's Underſtanding? But there is no ſuch
thing ſaid of God throughout the Word, but St. <hi>Paul</hi> to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Covenant, ſaid, that he
ſpake after the manner of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>;
though it be but a Man's Covenant, yet if it be confirmed, no Man
diſanulleth, it <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.15. But our Reformers had done well, if they
had ſaid there was a great Secret in the Word, which as yet they underſtand
not, and that it was not to be medled with till the Lord did give more Light,
ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording<pb n="94" facs="tcp:93759:42"/>to his Promiſe, before the time of the end; and
not to have ſet the Scriptures by their miſtaken Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, at an
unreconcileable Difference, as they have done; or it would have been much
better to have thought that when the Falſe Teachers had ingroſs'd the Word
into their own Hands, that they might have put in ſome words to make the New
Teſtament appear to contradict the Old, in what God had poſitively
Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed and Sworn to therein; ſeeing that God had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted Man with
the Word for his Poſterity, as <hi>Adam</hi> was intruſted with Eternal
Life for his Poſterity; the one being forbidden to Eat of the Tree, and the
other, that they ſhould neither add to, nor diminiſh from the Word,
<hi>Gen.</hi> 2.16,17. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.18,19.</p>
            <p>But as a Reverend and Worthy Dr. ſaid, That when the Reformers
firſt came out of Popery, they did plainly ſee that the Papiſts were
wrong, but they themſelves did not underſtand how to come right; and
indeed, in loſing the true meaning of the Word, it was a hard matter ſo to
do. But now God according to his Promiſe, has cauſed Light to break forth
at Evening time, <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.7. And has removed the occaſion of
Miſtakes, that thereby Knowledge might be increaſed, whereby the God of
Truth is made plainly appear to ſpeak Truth, as he is Truth, and that he will
do in all things accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as he has ſaid; who having employed and enabled a
weak Worm to vindicate his Truth and Juſtice to the Glory of his Name, and
the Comfort of Mankind. Now ſuch as will ſtand up to vindicate their
falſe received Notions, thereby to make the God of Truth, a Lyar, let them
take what will follow for their Pains; I am ſure that the honeſt Heart will
be glad that the Truth of God's Word is made plain, and his Honour therein
Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated. I underſtand that ſome of the Honourable of the Clergy of the
Church of <hi>England</hi> are well-wiſhers to the Truth, and the
ſoundeſt in the common Faith, (in<pb n="95" facs="tcp:93759:42"/>the Knowledge of which
is our Intereſt) are part of the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants, part of the
Church of <hi>England,</hi> the <hi>Daniſh</hi> and <hi>Swediſh</hi>
Miniſters, and the Baptiſts that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that Chriſt Died for the
World; I am not to ſpeak for Favour or Affection, but as the Truth is in
Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus according to the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>A Papiſt told me that the Church of <hi>England</hi> gave the
Sacrament as the Body and Blood of Chriſt, the which I denied, for though
they give indeed the Bread and Wine in the words of Chriſt; yet they do not
give it as his real Body, but as his Figurative Body, as Chriſt did when he
was ſetting whoſe with them at the Table; for the Lord was no otherwiſe
broken in the Sacrament, than he was Slain in the Paſchal Lamb, yet he was
ſaid to be Slain in that Sacrifice; but what great Miſtakes has it caus'd
the Chriſtians to be in, becauſe they and we have loſt the right
Apprehenſion of the Scripture way of ſpeaking.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="18" type="chapter">
            <head>XVIII. An account of the Lord's five times Hiring La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers
into his Vincyard.</head>
            <p>WHereas the Lord ſaith, 
<q rend="inline">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.1,2. 'The Kingdom of Heaven is
like unto a Man that is an Houſholder, which went out early in the Morning to
Hire Labourers into his Vineyard, and when he had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed with the Labourers,
he ſent them into his Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard.'</q> In the firſt place we are to take
notice by the Compariſon, that every time the Lord hired Labourers to work in
his Vineyard, he came forth from Heaven and Hired them, that is, Agreed or
Covenanted with them himſelf, as with <hi>Noah,</hi> and likewiſe with
<hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and alſo with <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Wilderneſs; and
ſo Chriſt when he Eſtabliſhed the Goſpel, the Agreement was, that all
that were Hired were to Work in the Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, and to have a Reward for their
Labour. And at the laſt time when the Lord comes forth, which will be 
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:93759:43"/>at the eleventh Hour, them that he then calls in at the
laſt Hour to Labour in his Vineyard, will be <hi>Iſrael</hi> when he again
comes, who then will be brought home by Repentance, when 
<q rend="inline">'they ſee him whom they Pierced,' <hi>Zach.</hi>
12.10.</q> 
               <q rend="inline"> 'For then ſhall they come with Weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and
with Supplications,' <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.9.</q> 
               <q rend="inline">'And then will the Lord cauſe them to walk in a
ſtraight way, wherein they ſhall not ſtumble,' verſe 9.</q> For then
will the Lord Eſtabliſh his now promiſed new everlaſting Covenant, and
then will the Labourers in the Vineyard be alike Rewarded, being made Partakers
of one and the ſame Covenant, the which will Crown life to the Soul. But let
not the Chriſtians be offended at that, but let them remember, that when
<hi>Iſrael</hi> for Sin was caſt out, then were the Sinners of the
<hi>Gentiles</hi> taken in, becauſe they had not Sinned againſt that Light
the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers did; for the Lord was <hi>a light to lighten the Gentiles,</hi>
(before he was to be) <hi>the glory of his people Iſrael,</hi> Luke 2.32. And
therefore here the <hi>Gentiles</hi> are put down in the firſt place; and
whereas it is ſaid in the Goſpel, the Lord will come in the laſt day,
becauſe to us that are under the Goſpel, it will be our laſt day; for we
ſhall not then be called to work in the Vineyard, for we are then to be
brought to Judgment, and then them that are found in their Obedience, will be
made partakers of the Promiſes, and the Wicked among them Condemned in
Judgment to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e now threatened
Puniſhments; but for the Chriſtians that have not oppoſed the Truth, and
have not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> guilty of the Sins of
the Times, yet have not a Sup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>lative Love to the Lord Jeſus, as is required in a well grounded
Faith, according to the Promiſe; ſuch will be left out, and not be numbred
with them with whom the everlaſting Covenant will then be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed
when the Lord <hi>returns and builds again the taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle of David which is
fallen, that the reſidue of men may ſeek after the Lord, and all the
Gentiles upon whom his name<pb n="97" facs="tcp:93759:43"/>is called,</hi> Acts 15.16.17.
The word <hi>all</hi> in Scripture, doth not include the whole, and herein are
not included the <hi>Gentiles</hi> that belong to the everlaſting Covenant,
neither them that fall under the threatned Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And the Apoſtle had
here his Reference in this Text to the word of the Lord, <hi>Amos</hi> 9.11,12.
<hi>In that day will I raiſe up the tabernacle of David, that they may
poſſeſs the remnant of Edom, and all the Heathen which are call'd by my
name.</hi> This <hi>all</hi> is ſpoken as aforeſaid, after the good are
ſecured, and the bad Condemned; for the <hi>Lord will ſave the Tents of
Judah firſt,</hi> Zach. 12.7. That is, the Remnant, with all that are found
in their Obedience to Chriſt, by which they come in as Heirs to the
Promiſes by the Lion of the Tribe of <hi>Judah.</hi> For were it not ſo,
the Houſe of <hi>David</hi> would be the Head of the Houſe of
<hi>Judah,</hi> verſe 9. Now whereas it is ſaid, that the reſidue of Men
might ſeek after the Lord, and the <hi>Gentiles</hi> upon whom his Name is
called; the which muſt be thoſe <hi>Gentiles</hi> whom Chriſt compares to
the foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Virgins, who though they were Virgins, ſo as not to be guilty
of the Sins of the times; yet for want of a ſound or right Faith upon which
the promiſed Bleſſedneſs depends; the Lord therefore then ſaith he
knows them not, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25 12. And ſo thoſe that were, and might
have been firſt, will then become laſt; for the <hi>Heathen</hi> are plac'd
before them, and ſo will the Word of the Lord then be fulfilled, <hi>that the
laſt ſhall be firſt, and the firſt laſt, Matth.</hi> 19.9.30. That
is, the <hi>Gentiles</hi> that received the Goſpel, they were firſt, and
<hi>Iſrael</hi> laſt; but when Chriſt again, comes, <hi>Iſrael</hi>
ſhall be then firſt, and thoſe under the Goſpel, which have been as
fooliſh Virgins, ſhall be laſt; for then thoſe <hi>Gentiles</hi> all
that come not in to have a ſhare in the everlaſting Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, will be then
given to be Servants to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and Servants to them that are
<hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Servants, <hi>Joel</hi> 3.8. And when Satan is bound, and
afterwards looſed again,<pb n="98" facs="tcp:93759:44"/>their Off-ſpring lies liable to
Satan's Temptations, by whom they being deluded, will then be miſerably taken
off, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 28.22. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.9. And the Lord fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing the
ſad Condition the Chriſtians would be in that are found unprepared for his
coming; therefore the Lord charged them to be upon their Watch, as that day
might not overtake them at unawares. And God hath promiſed <hi>that knowledge
ſhould be increaſed at the time of the end,</hi> Dan. 12.4,9. And at
Evening time it ſhould be light, <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.7. For the <hi>viſion is
for an appointed time, but at the end it ſhall ſpeak and not lie, though it
tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, wait for it, becauſe it ſhall ſurely come,</hi> Hab. 2.3. The
knowledge of this Viſion the Chriſtians ought to have retained, but being
loſt, God now of his great Mercy according to his Promiſe hath again
brought to light; the which Viſion we are now to wait for; or how will
<hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Conſtancy in waiting for the Promiſes made to their
Fathers appear for an Evidence to Condemn us who were to have a ſhare with
them in thoſe Promiſes? for the Door that is now open to all that will lay
hold of the offered Mercy to come in Heirs to the promiſed Covenant will then
be ſhut to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Chriſtians will then be
Condemned; for then will be the laſt day of the Goſpel Inſtitution, and
likewiſe the laſt day of the Power of this wicked World, ſo as their time
will be no longer. And why is it foretold that <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael's</hi> Return
ſhould be in the latter days, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 3.5. And their Glory then
<hi>when the mountain of the Lord's houſe ſhall be eſtabliſhed in the
top of the mountains;</hi> God thereby ſhewing that their bleſſed time
was a great diſtance off; for the Goſpel Inſtitution was to come in
between, and be ended before their bleſſed time would be, which was a
Secret hid in God from the Fathers, how the <hi>Gentiles</hi> or true
Chriſtians ſhould be brought in Heirs with <hi>Iſrael;</hi> for it was
but darkly Propheſied by the Prophets. But when the appointed time that the 
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:93759:44"/>Lord had determined for the <hi>Gentile</hi> Power, and
Goſpel Inſtitution, and that their time ſhould be no longer than till the
Lord cometh, who is repreſented to ſtand upon the Sea, and upon the Earth,
<hi>Rev.</hi> 10.5,6. <hi>But in the days of the voice of the ſeventh angel
when he ſhall begin to ſound, the myſtery of God ſhall be finiſhed,
as he hath declared to his ſervants the Prophets,</hi> verſe 7. For then
will this whole Myſtery of God be compleated; for the Saints will then be
raiſed, and then <hi>Iſrael</hi> will remain no longer ſcattered. So
accordingly it is ſaid, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.7. <hi>When he ſhall have
accompliſhed to ſcatter the power of the holy people; all theſe things
ſhall be finiſhed;</hi> and again, <hi>hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto is the end of the
matter,</hi> Dan. 7.28. Of this Viſion, which did appertain to this
Myſtery, which has to this day been hid from <hi>Iſrael. And Daniel heard,
but underſtood not; therefore ſaid, O my Lord what ſhall be the end of
theſe things? And the Lord ſaid, go thy way Daniel, for the words are
cloſed up and ſealed till the time of the end,</hi> verſe 8.9. And the
Diſciples asked the Lord why he ſpake to the <hi>Jews</hi> in Parables; the
Lord ſaid to them, <hi>It is given unto you to know the myſteries of the
king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of heaven, but to them it is not given,</hi> Matth. 13.10,11. For
indeed this Kingdom of Heaven, or Heavenly Kingdom, is a great Myſtery, which
when the Chriſtians had loſt the knowledg of this Secret, it was then to
remain a Secret till the time of the end; and now is the time the Lord will
have it Revealed, and they that deſire ſpiritual Wiſdom ſhall
underſtand it. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.10. And the Lord will firſt come in the
Clouds of Heaven, before the laſt or ſeventh Angel ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,
<hi>Matth.</hi> 24.31,32. And the Saints that are under the Altar receive white
Robes, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.9. In which they will accompany the Lord into the world
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their Bodies are raiſed, and then will the Nations know the two
Witneſſes, which now they underſtand<pb n="100" facs="tcp:93759:45"/>not. And all
this is to be after the Lord comes, and before the ſeventh Angel ſoundeth,
<hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15. And when <hi>the ſeventh Angel ſounded, there were
great Voices in Heaven, Saying, the kingdoms of this world are become the
kingdoms of our Lord, and of his Chriſt, and he ſhall reign for ever and
ever.</hi> And the Saints receiving their Bodies at the ſound of the laſt
or ſeventh Trumpet, (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.52.) the <hi>Elders fell upon their
faces and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed God,</hi> Rev. 11.16. But our Predeceſſors having
loſt the right Apprehenſion of theſe things, by reaſon of the
Apoſtacy; ſo as they that came after did not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand how God could
make his Promiſe good to the raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Saints, in providing Manſions in the
Heavens for them in that Tabernacle which the Lord ſhall pitch, and not Man;
at which time the Lord will reſtore <hi>Iſrael</hi> to their own Land.
Likewiſe, then God will make good his Word concerning the <hi>Heathen,</hi>
ſo as all the Families of the Earth ſhall be bleſſed in Chriſt, after
the wilfully Wicked are Condemned, accordingly as God hath threatened that he
would ſend his Angel and gather out of his Kingdom all things that offend, as
I have fully proved. For God by the Law and Goſpel, ſpeaks but to them that
are under it, and they are the World, and Heavens and Earth that will be
Condemned by it, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 34. <hi>Chap.</hi> 24 5,6. <hi>For
tranſgreſſing the laws, changing the ordinances, breaking the
everlaſting covenant, therefore the curſe devoureth the earth;</hi> that
is, the Earth upon whom the Curſe falls for the Offences. For the Ordinances
which St. <hi>Paul</hi> would have the Church keep, as they were delivered unto
them, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. God by this Prophet declares they have changed. And
in <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 34.18. it is ſaid, they have eaten the good Paſtures,
which muſt be thoſe Ordinances which <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith they have
changed; that is, put them away, and made new ones in their room; that is, new
Articles of Faith, new Church Government, new ways of Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring 
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:93759:45"/>the Sacraments; in all theſe things the Romiſh Church
is horribly out of the way, beſides all their other Abominations; and
likewiſe others as to ſome of theſe things will be found dangerouſly
out of the way, for treading down with their Feet the Reſidue of their
Paſtures, and alſo <hi>fouling of the deep waters with their feet, ſo as
the flock eat that which they have trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with their feet, and drink that
which they have fouled with their feet, verſe</hi> 18.19. This place, and the
fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mention'd Chapters of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> have peculiar Referen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to the
ſecond coming of Chriſt to Judgment, at which time he will Judge between
Cattel and Cattel, and the Rams and the hee Goats, <hi>v.</hi> 17. And then the
Lord will feed his Sheep himſelf, <hi>ſo as then they ſhall no more be a
prey when he is Prince among them, verſe</hi> 22.23,24. and the offending
Shepherds will God then feed with Judgment.</p>
            <p>But after the Teachers of the Romiſh Church had changed the
Ordinances, or eaten the good Paſtures, or, as the Lord ſaith, hid the
Talent; they thereby made way to ſet up their own Inſtitutions, and ſo
tranſgreſſed the Laws, and brake the everlaſting Covenant; for the
moral Law is an everlaſting Covenant, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 24.5. as well as the
new Covenant, when Eſtabliſhed, will be an everlaſting Covenant to them
with whom it is E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed; for the old Covenant will only then be done
away as a conditional Covenant, as now it is; for the Lord will then give an
inherent perfect Righteouſneſs to all with whom that Covenant will then be
made, as thereby they ſhall be enabled perfectly to keep the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Law; for
then God will <hi>magnifie the Law, and make it Honourable,</hi> Iſaiah
42.21. But when the Nations came to have no love to the Truth, and their Rulers
would not any longer be holden with the Cords of the Laws of the Lord,
according as it was Propheſied of, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 2. Then God permitted the
Prince of Darkneſs<pb n="102" facs="tcp:93759:46"/>to hoiſt up the Beaſt, an
Inſtrument whom Satan had prepared for his purpoſe, <hi>who thought to
change times and laws, and they were given into his hands till the day of
judgment, and then ſhall his dominion be taken away,</hi> Dan. 7.25,26. But
God all along preſerved the Law, and the Teſtimony of the Prophets ſafe
in the Hands of the <hi>Jews,</hi> whom he ſcattered throughout the World,
that they might be a Light to the World in the cloudy and dark Day, when the
Beaſt had deprived the Nations of the reſt of the Scriptures; and the
Chriſtians knowing that Chriſt was come, and that the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial Law was
Aboliſhed, and that Chriſt was that great Sacrifice that had made an
Attonement for Sins that were paſt, for all thoſe that would walk in
Obedience to the reſt of God's Laws and Commands and Precepts, that Chriſt
would then compleat their ſincere Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, (they not forgetting Baptiſm
and the Lord's Supper.) For all the Prophets as they declare Chriſt firſt
coming to Suffer, ſo alſo they declare that he will come again to Judge and
Reign. And in the way of well-doing, God has declared by the Prophets, that we
may ſtay our ſelves upon his Promiſes, in that he will ſhew his
Salvation to all that walk uprightly by their improving the Day of Grace
whilſt it was in their Hands, that they might not be hardned through the
Deceitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Sin, by accuſtoming themſelves therein; which had the
Chriſtians taken heed to the Law and to the Prophets, herein they could have
been very little out of the way; 'for whoſoever ſpeaks not according to the
Law and the Teſtimony of the Prophets, it is becauſe there is no light in
them, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 8.20. But many be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deceived by the Popiſh
Idolatrous Worſhip, and with their pretended Pardons; and alſo many others
by truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to an Election, that to themſelves they have Fram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and
others by expecting to be ſaved by the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Chriſt,
contrary to the words of Chriſt,<pb n="103" facs="tcp:93759:46"/>which is in the way of
their ſincere Obedience; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Millions of poor Chriſtians being thus
deluded, are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep in ſecurity, by which miſerable miſtaken Notions
the generality of the Chriſtians are become worſe than Heathens. Which if
they are not well awakened and brought off of their ſandy Foundation, the
generality of the Proteſtant Chriſtians, as well as the Papiſt, will cry
out of their Leanneſs, <hi>the treacherous dealers have dealt very
treacherouſly,</hi> Iſaiah 24.16. when they find themſelves wanting, both
of ſound Knowledge and good Fruit when their Deſtruction cometh. And let
all that have pretended to be God's pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar and elect People when they are
not; conſider what it is to Exalt themſelves into that Station or Place
into which God hath not put them, by the Example of them that ſo did, and
were deſtroyed for ſo doing, <hi>Numb.</hi> 16. For did either God or
Chriſt ever threaten Damnation to any that did not think themſelves
Elected? Or did they only promiſe Salvation to them that were Elected? Sure
we find no ſuch thing in the Word of God, but the promiſed eternal
Salvation, both in the Old and New Teſtament, is to them that obey him, fear
before him, walk uprightly, and fervently love him and believe his Word, and
cannot think that he will be falſe, or a Deceiver; but that God will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form
his Promiſe to all according to his Word; and according to his Word it will
be that the Tranſgreſſors under the Law and Goſpel, will fall under the
threatned Condemnation. For the <hi>Gentiles</hi> as well as the <hi>Jews,</hi>
when their Prophets and Rulers, which are their Seers, became weary of the Ways
or Laws of the Lord, one was left to Blindneſs, the other to Deluſion; by
which we may ſee the Word of God made good in both, and in the New
Teſtament the Teachers are likewiſe called Prophets, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.4.
And it is ſaid, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 29.10. <hi>The Lord hath poured out upon
you the ſpirit of deep ſleep,<pb n="104" facs="tcp:93759:47"/>and hath cloſed your
eyes, the Prophets and your Rulers; the Seers hath he covered, and the viſion
of all is become unto you, as the words of a book that is ſealed.</hi> Now in
that this Viſion is termed the Viſion of all; therefore it hath its chief
Reference to Chriſt's ſecond coming, the which is ſet down to be a
Viſion, and that <hi>at the end it ſhould ſpeak,</hi> Hab. 2.3. The which
both <hi>Jews</hi> and Chriſtians were commanded to wait for. But becauſe
the Rulers and Teachers of both were the firſt occaſion of laying the World
in Darkneſs, therefore God hath declared he hath covered them, ſo as this
Viſion they were not to be the firſt diſcoverers of. And though
doubtleſs when Chriſt firſt came, there were ſome good Rulers and good
Prieſts among them, ſo I hope there are many more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us
Chriſtians now. But God by bringing out the Truth in an unexpected way, doth
thereby carry on the Counſel of his own Will, which is never without a
Reaſon; and <hi>God ſaith he knoweth the proud afar off.</hi> And therefore
that ſuch may be ſnared, he brings to light the Knowledge of his Truth by
an unexpected Hand; by reaſon of which, ſome had rather go without the
Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Truth, than ſo receive it. But let the Wiſe in Heart
conſider it, that the Ignorant by their Example may come out of their
Miſtakes now God has made the Viſion clear, that the thinking Soul may not
be taken in the Snare. For this Viſion in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 29.7. hath its
reference to the time to come, when all that have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſt <hi>Ariel,</hi>
ſhall be but as a Dream of a Night Viſion, they ſhall ſo paſs away.
And this ſealed Viſion, ſpoken of in the 11 verſe, is the Viſion in
the <hi>Revelations,</hi> which has been Sealed unto us, for we have not
underſtood it; and this Viſion which God by the Prophet ſaith is become
Sealed; gives us to underſtand that it was not always ſo; for when the
Goſpel was firſt Eſtabliſhed, this Goſpel of the Kingdom was one of
the fundamental Doctrins; who when the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles<pb n="105" facs="tcp:93759:47"/>had
firſt fed their Converts <hi>with Milk, they</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>fed them
with ſtrong Meat,</hi> in declaring to them all the Counſel of God,
<hi>Acts</hi> 20.26. But afterward the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians did Apoſtatize from the
Truth, and did ſet up their own Imaginations, and would have in this time a
tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Kingdom of Chriſt. And when they thus grew weary of the Truth of
God's Word, then God Vail'd or covered their Underſtanding, ſo as they
could not appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the glorious Kingdom of Chriſt, which will be here in
time to come.</p>
            <p>And after this the Viſion again became Sealed, and then neither
the Learned, nor Unlearned could Read it. But God often chuſes to ſhew
forth his Power through the weakneſs of the Inſtrument, and on that ſide
by whom this Offence was not committed. And thoſe that refuſe the Truth,
becauſe it comes forth by a Woman, may as well refuſe to be ſaved by
Chriſt, becauſe he came by a Woman. For God carries on his Works in one and
the ſame Method; for as when <hi>Iſrael</hi> was brought out of
<hi>Aegypt</hi> to go into the promiſed Land, the Glory of the Lord was then
in the Clouds; ſo it will be again when the Lord comes, and much more
abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly; and alſo as Chriſt firſt came by a Woman, ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain after
the Lord aroſe, he 'then appeared firſt to a Women, and likewiſe when
Chriſt was firſt brought in to the Temple to be Offered to the Lord, then
of all them that had their Abode in the Temple, it was a Woman among them that
did there firſt acknowledge him to be the Redeemer, to ſuch <hi>that look
for redemption in Iſrael,</hi> Luke 2.38. But that God that carries on his
Works in a way of Method, that the thinking Soul may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it, will not
now contradict himſelf by leaving the Method that he formerly took.</p>
            <p>And now the Viſion is made ſo plain to any that has a Rational
Underſtanding, that according to the Word, he that runs may Read it; and
therefore we are to<pb n="106" facs="tcp:93759:48"/>wait, <hi>for at the end it will
ſpeak and not lie,</hi> Hab. 2.3. And now likewiſe the Old and New
Teſtament are made to agree, and all the occaſions of the Miſtakes are
removed, that thereby <hi>knowledge might be increaſed at the time of the
end,</hi> Dan. 12.4. And this now the Lord having made good according to his
Word, at the time of the end; the which is a greater Evidence, than if Angels
had come from Heaven and declared it, if they had not from the Word made it
plain; becauſe we are not to receive any other Doctrin, than what was firſt
taught from the Teſtimony of Prophets and Apoſtles; ſo as had not this
been made plain from the Word, it would have appeared another Doctrin, and ſo
not to have been believed, becauſe the evil Angels can Transform themſelves
into Angels of Light, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.14. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8. And we were to
receive nothing in contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction to <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets,
<hi>Luke</hi> 16.31. But God will carry on his work according to his word.</p>
            <p>As for any to expect the Spirit to be poured out upon them, to
prepare them for the coming of the Lord, is a great Miſtake, and the Prince
of Darkneſs would gladly perſwade any to believe that; for by that belief
he keepeth them from preparing themſelves, that thereby they may be taken at
unawares, for Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan has many Wiles to deceive poor Souls. For the Chriſtians
will not have the Spirit poured out upon them, before the Lord comes to prepare
them, no more than <hi>Iſrael</hi> had when the Lord firſt came; for if
ſo, the Lord would not have commanded them to be upon <hi>their watch, leſt
coming ſuadenly he ſhould find them ſleeping.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="19" type="chapter">
            <head>XIX. Chriſt ſaying all Power was given of the Father,
Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained.</head>
            <p>WHereas Chriſt ſaid after he aroſe, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.18.
<hi>All power is given to me in heaven and in earth.</hi>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:93759:48"/>That was, he then had paid the purchaſe of it; and he was then as
really aſſured of it, as though he had it in Poſſeſſion, having the
Promiſe of God for it. And it is the Scriptures uſual way of ſpeaking, to
mention things that are to come, as though they were then preſent.
Accordingly God ſaid to <hi>Abraham,</hi> I have made thee a Father of many
Nations, at which time he was not Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of one Child. But God having
promiſed, it was certainly to come to paſs, and therefore ſpoken as then
done, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.17. According to which Chriſt
ſpake; for it is the World to come that is to be put in ſubjection unto
him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5. And when the ſeventh Angel ſoundeth, then it is the
<hi>kingdoms of this world are become the kingdoms of our Lord, and of his
Chriſt, and he ſhall reign for ever and ever,</hi> Rev. 11.15. When he hath
taken to him <hi>his own great power,</hi> verſe 17. I hope the Chriſtians
will conſider theſe great Truths, that they may not be found upon a falſe
bottom. For God doth not now compel, but chalk out the way, and leaves Man to
chuſe, or refuſe to obey. But in the day of his Power, he will again pour
forth his Spirit; for the firſt Churches had but a foretaſt of the
earneſt of that Inheritance, which his People will partake of when the Lord
again comes, World without end. And then his People <hi>Iſrael</hi> will be
made a willing People, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 110.3. When he removeth the Iniquity of
that Land in one day, in that day ſhall they call every Man under his Vine,
and under his Fig-tree, <hi>Zach.</hi> 3.9,10. Then it is the two Olive-trees,
will give out of themſelves the Golden Oyl of Grace and Wiſdom into the
Candleſtick that is all of Gold, Chap. 4.2. And then the Lord will make his
Church a glorious Church without Spot or Wrinkle, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.27. But now
the beſt of Saints are not without Sin, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.8. I thought at
this time to have given a full Satisfaction who theſe two Olive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trees were,
who in the New Teſtament are termed two<pb n="108" facs="tcp:93759:49"/>Witneſſes,
who all along have accompanied the Church or Woman in the Wilderneſs, who
according to Promiſe had never been deceived by Beaſt or falſe Prophet.
And theſe two Witneſſes always accompanying her, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid to be
cloathed in Sackcloath, in bearing part of her Afflictions with her; as it was
formerly ſaid of Chriſt; that in all his Peoples Afflictions, he was
Afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 63.9. And alſo it is ſaid, the holy Spirit
may be grieved. For theſe two Olive-trees, which in this time are ſaid to
be the two Witneſſes, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.3,4. and alſo elſewhere in the
Scripture they are often ſo called; and theſe two Witneſſes we may
readily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve can do all thoſe Miracles, Cited in the 5 and 6 Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;
whereas it is ſaid in the 8 Verſe, <hi>their dead Bodies.</hi> Now this
being ſpoken of the Remnant, to whom the Lord promiſed to be with to the
end of the World, and that he would ſend them another Comforter, that
ſhould abide with them for ever, as is at large in the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Cloathed with
the Sun prov'd. And when theſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons become ſo oppreſt by the
Beaſt, as Scattered, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, and Slain, theſe two Witneſſes
cannot then by them bear their Teſtimony againſt the Evil of Sin, and the
Pernicious Idolatrous Worſhip of the Beaſt; and thus the two Witneſſes
are ſaid to be dead, when their Bodies are thus Slain, ſo as they cannot by
them bear their Teſtimony; whoſe dead Bodies were again to ſtand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
their Feet. As to what I have here but hinted con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them, to give ſome
Light herein, I thought to have fully proved, and to have made clearly appear
who this fore mentioned Beaſt is. But having many other things to anſwer,
my time would not permit me, at this preſent. O that we had but a Heart to
conſider the greater Truths of God, whoſe Faithfulneſs cannot fail,
according to his Word; for which bleſſed be his Name, World without end.
<hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
